<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bloody Babylon discoverd</title>
            <author>[Londinatus, Christianus].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1928_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868834</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868834</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 239:E1928[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bloody Babylon discoverd</title>
                  <author>[Londinatus, Christianus].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Christianus Londinatus" is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 6.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121190:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BLOODY BABYLON DISCOVERD. Or, the Myſtery of Iniquity Reveal'd, <hi>Written long ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Information of <hi>Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> in generall; more particularly intended for that once <hi>Famous Flouriſhing,</hi> and, for Civill <hi>Government,</hi> Admired Honourable City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By CHRISTIANUS LONDINATUS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Melius eſt inter Barbaros ſub ſpecie Captivitatis eſſe liber, quàm ſub ſpecie liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atis eſſe Captivus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Salv. de gub. Dei.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quaerendum eſt mihi apud Barbaros Angliae humanitatem, quia apud Anglos barbaram inhumanitatem ferre non Poſſum.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Salv.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If thou warne the Wicked, and he turne not from his wickedneſſe, nor from his wicked way, he ſhall dye in his Iniquity, but thou haſt delivered thy ſoul.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> Chap. 3. verſ. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:121190:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121190:2"/>
            <head>The Myſtery of Iniquity <hi>REVEAL'D.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Compaſſionate bowells of a tenderly-affecting father toward his Sonnes (though refractorie, in their demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; un-naturall in their returns of expreſſive unſonne-like diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for his dear expreſſions of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-like affection) ſtill continue woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with intermixed ſighs and tears, thoſe obſtinately wicked Children, (Nature working, as it were againſt Nature) his naturall affection, as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prevailing over his angry inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by nature as a man; with weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rhetorick, perſwading their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from thoſe ſelf-deſtroying paths: By ſuch winning meanes, inviting them, to the avoiding of approaching
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121190:3"/>miſery, and injoyment of their almoſt irrecoverably lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t felicity.</p>
            <p>Even ſo, (Notwithſtanding theſe lines, like that paſſionately wooing-father, onely aime at the temporall and eternall happineſſe, of all thoſe, (whoſe paſt and preſent worſt of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo Obvious to the World's eye, need not, <hi>argito Monſtrari,</hi> plainer words to ſpeak the concern'd Perſons) becauſe for theſe lines alone, I cannot but expect, to be met with by Envy (ſo unwilling, guilty men are to read their Crimes, though but in a ſilently ſpeaking line); purſued by Malice (ill requitall for really Conferr'd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to return diſcourteous perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quution); and overtaken by bloody re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, though perchance, palliated with that falſe and cheating veile of new-minted Law and Juſtice, (ſtrange men to endeavour the ruine of thoſe, whoſe endeavours tend onely to the preſervation of them from Ruine!)</p>
            <p>My inward thoughts, Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe Contrary perſwading dangers; inhumane and un-chriſtian requitalls; inclined me to a paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Compaſſion of my deareſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121190:3"/>ſtill (by the prevailing rule-leſſe, over-ruling, bloodily-deſtroying facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that head-leſſe, diſmembred thing, falſely ſtyled <hi>Parliament,</hi> with the additionall treachery of ſome ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid paſſiveneſſe of others) graſping thoſe flames which already have ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly deſtroyed their once flouriſhing peace, conſumed their formerly-hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py government, into an aſhy heap, and ere long unavoidably will render each particular man, abounding in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but in the aboundance of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; wanting ſtore of all things, but of want; unhappy, even beyond the addition of greater unhappineſſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already become Obedientiall ſlaves to the peremptory Commands, Wills, and Pleaſures of irrationall, irreligious, lawleſs, blood thirſty, and Sacrilegious men; theſe having, under unjuſt pretences of freeing them from a former falſely-ſuppoſed tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, freed them from hopes of being what formerly, (by vertue of the Law's Protection) they were, Free-men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, by the aſſiſtance of the God of Heaven, who is my ſhield,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121190:4"/>buckler, and defence, now even while it is yet day; before the approaching night of darkneſſe over-ſpread theſe three Kingdomes, with a generall Cloud of deſtruction; I ſhall, (by drawing the Curtain of errour, which hath overcaſt the Judgments of the moſt, even to the viſible deprivation of that diſtinguiſhing Character be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men and beaſts, REASON) endeavour <hi>hominem homini oſtendere,</hi> ſhew unreaſonable man, himſelfe in the glaſſe of reaſon again; diſpelling alſo that thick Miſty veyl of Atheiſm, (for it is no better, let them give it what ſeeming<note n="*" place="margin">The Cauſe of God.</note> Saint-like Title they pleaſe) which many, with as much boaſting Confidence put on, as if it were the white Robes of Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. The Pulpit too often wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully declaring the irregular faction of that Monſtrous <hi>Houſe,</hi> impudently Promulgating Painted Truths, which indeed are no other than reall falſities, and many people (but I hope ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) embracing them inſtead of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall verities, being lead by theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</note> Lights, which like the laſt blaze of a ſpent Taper, quickly vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121190:4"/>leaves them as loſt men in the dark, in ſtead of that glorious Sun of Light, (Chriſt Jeſus) whoſe unmixt pure beams, apparent onely in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will, (the holy Scriptures) are the directing means, able alone to guide them to that celeſtiall place, where there is eternity of light for evermore.</p>
            <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdoms (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe many <hi>Recipe's</hi> for ſpirituall diſeaſes, left us by the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian of our ſouls in the Cabinet of the Scriptures, and theſe repeated in almoſt a daily application by true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divines, his faithfull ſervants) continue ſtill ſick of obſtinately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſive ſins, which, like inſenſibility of a diſeaſe in a diſeaſed man, is a ſure preſage of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>I ſhall, by reviving ſome medicines proper for our preſent diſtemper (for what are truely-Orthodox Books, but like Phyſick to conſuming bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as ſo many reſtoratives to a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Nation?) endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of them to a re-poſſeſſion of their former peace, now breathing their laſt: The re-enjoyment of truth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121190:5"/>Goſpell-truth, loſt almoſt under a confuſed heap of Hereticall, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, and Atheiſticall errours; and the return of their not-long ſince ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired plenty, now declining into a neceſſitous, and almoſt unavoidable poverty.</p>
            <p>But becauſe man is but a dully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading Orator, unleſſe the God of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits ſpeak effectually alſo to their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate hearts; Therefore,</p>
            <p>O thou Omnipotent, Omniſcient, All-working Lord God, the fountain from whence ſtreameth every good thing, in whoſe hands are the hearts of all men, and canſt turn and wind them at thy pleaſure; Cauſe all the people of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to return unto Thee, by an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiall ſubſcription to thy everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting truth, and a practicall obedience according to its direction: In ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for their hearts of ſtone, give them, O Lord, hearts of fleſh, molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd by thy gently, yet prevalently, malleating Spirit. Throw down all thoſe bulwarks of prejudice, raiſed againſt the truth of Reaſon, and the reaſon of thy religious Truth. Levell,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121190:5"/>O levell, thoſe high-built Forts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe reſolves, wilfully to perſiſt in ill-begun courſes, becauſe ſucceſſe for a time waits upon attempts; as if the commanding bloody Sword had (by its prevalency) power as eaſie to create new commandements, and evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call truths, as by treachery, diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, tyranny, and oppreſſion, it hath had, to overthrow an antient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and, as if a ſhort proſperity in wickedneſſe were the certain mark of thoſe that travell in the high way to eternal happineſſe: When as thou, O Lord, haſt ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 92.7</note> that <hi>though the wicked ſpring as graſs, and the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity do flouriſh, yet they ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ever?</hi> Summon them by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually ſounding Trumpet of thy Spirit, to a condeſcention to thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will and pleaſure, which is but their reaſonable ſervice; and cauſe their return'd anſwers to ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but, O Lord God moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, we proſtrate our ſelves at thy feet, and confeſſe our former number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe number of ſins, of rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee our God, in ſleighting thy precepts, in fighting againſt thine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121190:6"/>Servant, our Soveraign and ſupream Governour the King; in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying our fellow-ſubjects, their perſons and eſtates, which we ſhould have preſerved, offending contrary to the principles of our Religion, the practice and commands of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the eſtabliſhed Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> For all which, we repent, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, we repent, and caſt our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy arms of mercy. Thus do, good Father, to all ſuch, who have erred and gone aſtray from thy paths; and this even before thy battering decree, for an everlaſting deſtruction both of ſoul and body, iſſueth forth. And all this grant for the onely merits of thy Son, our Saviour, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Becauſe in the originall of this bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Rebellion, the plot (like the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and, untill now, unparallel'd-<hi>Powder-plot</hi>)<note n="*" place="margin">Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> was laid ſo deep under ground, covered over with more ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly innocent materialls, to make it thereby more inviſible to the eye, That indeed being intentionally this very deſigne acted; and this, but that conſpiracy actually effected. In the firſt were combining Papiſts, figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121190:6"/>under the bloody Banner, and obeying the commands of Antichriſt, the Pope. In the ſecond are preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Proteſtants, being ſuch onely, <hi>nomine, non re,</hi> making uſe of the ſame Papiſticall and Antichriſtian bloody principles, means, and method; both of them obedient children of the ſame father of lies, the devill, and enemies to the Goſpell of Chriſt Jeſus. In the firſt, they reſolved at one blow, by their ſuddenly conſuming powder, to deſtroy <hi>Rem, Regem, Regimen, Regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Religionem;</hi> but execution was, by the miraculous mercy of the God of Heaven, prevented. In the ſecond, <hi>Theſe,</hi> with a kind of unthought-of whiter Powder, (Pretences of a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Reformation, and ſetting Chriſt upon his Throne, <hi>Chriſti nomine arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, tamen con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra Chriſtum dimicantes</hi>) have, by the permisſion of the ſame God, now diſpleaſed and angry with a ſinfull people, actually brought to paſſe; and accordingly have ruined the King's Majeſty, deſtroyed our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Religion, Laws, and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But, <hi>How long, Lord, how long? wilt thou be angry for ever? ſhall thy jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121190:7"/>burn like fire? See, O Lord, we are all thy people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 64.9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>thy holy Cities are a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, Zion and Jeruſalem are a deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Our holy and our beautifull hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where our fathers praiſed thee, are deſtroyed, and our pleaſant things laid waſte. O remember not againſt us former iniquities; let thy tender mercies ſpeedily prevent us, for we are brought very low.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe this Rebellious Deſigne in the beginning, was, I ſay, a myſtery to moſt of the common people, I ſhall now unveil it, that ſo all ſuch who formerly have been miſleadd, or ſtill ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly perſiſt in ſuch bloody waies, may return, repent, and do their firſt works, leſt God come againſt them in judgment in this world, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the reward of Traitors with <hi>Faulks, Percy,</hi> and their complices, here; or, with <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, be in an inſtant ſwallowed up into an eternal grave.</p>
            <p>Becauſe former, antient, and meer, or, if you will, Atheſticall Polititians, like your Water-men on the <hi>Thames,</hi> ſeldome or never directed their faces the ſame way they ſteered
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121190:7"/>their courſes, untill they were arriv'd at the pretended end of their ſhort voyage, their primarily reſolved ends: And in regard our modern Polititians have walked in the ſelf ſame paths, trode thoſe very ſteps, with this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition onely, that they have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all former Preſidents, in their exceſſive and accumulative wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, themſelves being become the onely black and bloody copies, for the imitation of the worſt of men in future ages: yet, if it be posſible, theſe times (which cannot eaſily find place in my belief) can produce a generation of men ſo impudently bad, that will not look pale, and ſtart at ſuch unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd patterns of ſuperlative villanies, reſerving choice of them for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary preſidents. For, in reſpect of compariſon,</p>
            <p>I challenge the whole world, ſince the reduction of the firſt rude Chaos into an orderly diviſion, untill this new Chaos of Anarchicall confuſion, in theſe daies of ours; Let the beſt travelling brain therein, whoſe buſie ſtudies have been onely Hiſtorically employ'd, in collecting the ſucceſſive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121190:8"/>vices of all generations; let him ſum up all thoſe collections, and out of them abſtract the quinteſſence of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and Ambition, the poyſon of Rebellion and Treaſon, the rancour of Envy and Hatred, the venome of malitious Murderers, and of all other <hi>conglomer ata facinora,</hi> monſtrous ſins, hainous crimes that ever were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and let him contract the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of all thoſe into one entire heap, nay, let him by his chymicall brain once more diſtill the quinteſſence of that hypocriticall and ambitious quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence, the poyſon of that treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and rebellious poyſon, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of that malitiouſly murdering venom: yet after all this, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon will not hold in the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. Theſe worſt and lateſt times, by their over-ballancing ponderous weighty crimes, will mount thoſe lighter faults of former ages into the aire. <hi>Tam ingenioſe ſumus literis diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis diſerti;</hi> men are grown ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficients in deſtructive bloody do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and diabolicall actions. Thus, Lord, are ſinners, by addition of ſin to ſin, and aggravation of that addition
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121190:8"/>by an obſtinately continuance therein, become incomparably ſinfull. But, Father of mercies, reward us not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our deſerts; but ſpare us, good Lord, ſpare thy people whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood.</p>
            <p>Now at laſt, and the better to make a progreſſion in my intended pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I ſhall ſhew you the method of theſe latter Polititians, ſtyling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians, agreeing with the former profeſſed Atheiſticall ones, with the premiſed addition, that theſe titular Chriſtians have out-ſtripp'd the antiquated Atheiſts, in their moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, hypocriticall, and bloody practiſes.</p>
            <p>To this end I ſhall, by a ſeeming way of propounding queſtions, give a reſolution to all unprejudiced eyes and ears in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>Can any age afford a people, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesſing ſo ſeemingly well, and acting ſo really deſperately ill?</p>
            <p>Review the then Petition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1642.</note> accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying that grand Remonſtrance, or rather that plotted foundation of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, laid purpoſely for other inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121190:9"/>ſuperſtructures, to cheat the common ſort of people into an asſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting conſpiracy; there you ſhall find them petitioning for the uniting of all loyall and obedient Subjects: Who are theſe? but Subjects by the Law decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſupream Governour, the King.</p>
            <p>Obedient Subjects, that joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame fundamentall truths, againſt a Popiſh faction, who had (as in the Declaration is pretended) a reſolution to alter the Religion of the Kingdom. Who can theſe be? but true Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> the onely prevailing parties againſt the Popiſh and Jeſuitized ſtrongeſt holds: Yet in their united actions, and doctrinall principles, how do theſe two factions joyn together againſt the reall Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, who onely maintain truths fundamentall againſt Jeſuiticall, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical, and Schiſmatical tenents; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the new-coined diſtinction of theſe Jeſuitized factious perſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kings Vertuall, and Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, how have they bawled out their pretences, of figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121190:9"/>for the Kings perſonall defence, yet brought Armies to fight againſt his Perſon; an Argument left onely to be maintain'd by the cruell, yet ſilly non-diſtinguiſhing Bullet, or others, as irrationall as it.</p>
            <p>How often have they in their Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets declared, that they onely took up Armes againſt his Majeſtie's evill Councell; when as they could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no witneſſe, nor example of any Counſell, that was evill, unleſſe it were ill for a man to be Rationall, a Chriſtian, or a Loyall Subject?</p>
            <p>How have they (Notwithſtanding their Declarations, of making him a moſt Glorious King, excelling all his Royall Predeceſſours,<note place="margin">First Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Ord. Par. <hi>F. 21.</hi>
               </note> Proteſting to maintain his Honour Crown and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, yet) baited him with Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons altogether deſtructive to his Honour and Power as a King;<note place="margin">19. <hi>Prop.</hi>
               </note> the end of their taking up of Armes, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring nothing leſſe then the end of their pretences. Unleſſe they intended thereby, (as indeed ſome of them have done) to make him a Glorious Saint in Heaven. And all this, nay more than this, acted, not by heathens, who knew
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121190:10"/>no better, nor by profeſſ'd Papiſts, whoſe rebelliouſly-religious Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples teach no better; but, by Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding-Proteſtants!</p>
            <p>O let not this be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor publiſhed in the ſtreets of <hi>Askelon;</hi> leſt the Daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce, and the Daughters of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed triumph.</p>
            <p>How have they rattled out Reſolves, to maintain the eſtabliſhed Lawes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>vid.</hi> Collect Ord. Parl.</note> eſpecially, that part thereof, which concerneth the liberty of the Subject? View all their Declarations; not one but ſpeaketh ſomewhat to that preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, how have they in the beginning, and progreſſion of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, trod down all appearance of Law? Witneſſe their unjuſt impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, Sequeſtrations, Taxes, and Exciſe, and many more illegall ſquee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Engins; Contracting the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of each particular ſubject by a written Law, his owne Right, into the narrow Compaſſe of ſome few mens unwritten Lawleſſe Wills; nay Is not the Liberties of Nineteen Parts of the People of Great Brittain, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121190:10"/>up by an One twentieth? who revell it in Libertiniſm, upon the Ruines of their liberties, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt poſſeſſion of the Eſtates. Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling<note n="*" place="margin">Englands liberties Confirmed.</note> 
               <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> ſo abſurdly in their furious and hot declarations, that, like Parchment againſt the fire, it is now ſhrunck up almoſt to a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appearance.</p>
            <p>How have ſome men of all degrees actively contributed their aſſiſtance in Men, Money and Plate, upon invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions literally different from the ends of theſe Eradicating Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours? although, I muſt acquaint them, upon no reall grounds of Reaſon, Religion, or Law; but my Charity telleth me, they were abuſed by ſuch ſpecious pretences, into ſuch ill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe that Ordinance of the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>January,</hi> 1641. whereby <hi>Skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon</hi> was made Serjeant Major Generall of London, who commanded the imployment of the Trained Bands for the reall (they are the words of that Ordinance) good Service of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, the Parliament and City; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Duty, Proteſtation, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121190:11"/>Lawes of the Land. —</p>
            <p>Fine words truly in appearance! but deeds lurking under, as black as hell. Witneſſe the progresſive and Concluſive part of their ugly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>19.</hi> Prop. Coll. Ord. Parl. <hi>pag. 173.</hi>
               </note> in their Declaration of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>May,</hi> 1642, concerning the Militia; all mens obedience is invited to the Execution of their Commands, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome; as they tender (ſaith that Ordinance) the upholding of the True Proteſtant Religion,</p>
            <p>The ſafety of his Majeſtie's Perſon —</p>
            <p>And his Royall Poſterity, with the Peace of the Kingdome —</p>
            <p>Alas! what fundamentall lawes do they mean? Aiery lawes ſurely! whoſe exiſtence is no where to be found, but in their meer verball aſſeverations; and that alſo in a reall oppoſition to thoſe Lawes, whoſe Eſtabliſhed foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation (as Lawes indeed ſhould) plainly appear to every Loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject's Obedientiall eye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True Proteſtant religion (ſaith the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance)</hi> — But more truly, Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Proteſtant religion, falſly by them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121190:11"/>ſtyled True; whoſe practicall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, overthrow the principles of all religious truth, and fight againſt the practicall piety of the true Proteſtant Religion Eſtabliſhed, and the practice of all the primitive Chriſtians, and truly-Chriſtian<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr. John Bradford.</hi> adviſed all to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Queen, and by no means to reſiſt. <hi>vid. Book Martyr. fol. 1491. 1477.</hi>
               </note> Martyrs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Safety of his Majeſties Perſon, and Royall iſſue!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dangerous ſafety of their Royall Perſons, whoſe ſecurity muſt depend on the ſure rock of Certain danger, oppoſing Armies (under pretence of their preſervation) with ready-drawn Swords, and ſurely-deſtroying bullets, endeavouring their abſolute ruine.</p>
            <p>O ſtrange Paper-protection, vaine and weak! from a pretended hazard, of being untimely deprived of life; thus to expoſe them to a reall danger, of an unnaturall Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peace.</hi>) Stranger peace! whoſe fruits muſt be a bloody war,<note place="margin">Ord.</note> and its effects nothing but murder, perjury, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, oppreſſion, tyranny, and, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, a generall poverty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kingdom.</hi> A dumb Kingdom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſpeaking King;<note place="margin">Ord.</note>) or rather, (to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound their then intended monſtrous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121190:12"/>ſenſe, myſticall onely to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people) a deformed Anarchy, in place of an unparalle'd Reformed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</p>
            <p>But, O Lord of Hoſts, that judgeſt righteouſly,<note place="margin">Jer. 11.20.</note> and tryeſt the reins and the heart, grant them ſuddain repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or let thy ſervants ſee thy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on all ſuch obſtinately perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſinners; for unto Thee I have, and ſhall, open Great-<hi>Brittain</hi>'s cauſe. Conſider,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 29.13.</note> O Father, how theſe people ſeem to come near to thee, the God of truth, with their mouth, and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee with their lips, but their hearts are far from thee.</p>
            <p>Again, In the Propoſitions and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the <hi>Two Houſes,</hi> (for as yet the<note n="*" place="margin">Presb. Indep.</note> Factions, like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained united in the bonds of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) for bringing in of Plate and Mony, to maintain Horſe, Horſemen, and Arms, &amp;c. you were all promiſed, (you, I mean, the contributers upon ſuch quaintly-deceiving invitations) that your mony, ſo brought in, ſhall onely be employ'd to maintain the Proteſtant Religion, the King's autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and his perſon in his royall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121190:12"/>
            <p>A free courſe of Juſtice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collect Ore. Parl.</hi> fol. 343. June 1642.</note> the Laws of the Land, and the Peace of the Kingdom— when as in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their Rooting deſigne, the irreligiouſly religious Turk and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, by their actions, may rather claim them as adherents to their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; nay, the Jeſuite embrace them as his deareſt dear obedientiall dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, than the Proteſtant Church of <hi>England</hi> own them as her children.</p>
            <p>The Kings Authority and Perſon after a retrograde manner by them maintained; their Ordinances, Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Oaths, and actions, ſpeaking a denyall of their obedience to the one, and but a verball protection one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the other; themſelves not then ſo much as allowing him the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting aſſiſtance from any of his loyall Subjects, whoſe religious conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe onely invited them to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of his royall Perſon. More than this, the Jeſuite himſelf could not have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Free courſe of Juſtice (that Ordinance promiſeth.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good God! what free courſe of Juſtice do they mean, when they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121190:13"/>themſelves obſtruct the freedom of all Juſtice? and amidſt their own conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations in publick, will not admit of any negative Reply, (though never ſo rationall and religious) which oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the free courſe of their bloody deſigne.</p>
            <p>What Law is their guide, whoſe practiſe oppoſeth all Law, both Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane? I need not inſert any exemplary particular proof; their own generall and palpably-known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſpeak themſelves ſufficiently guilty of oppoſing the Law of the Land, the current of whoſe ſenſe run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth contrary to their actions; not a line, almoſt, but enjoyneth the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, not a conditionall, as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, but an abſolute indiſpenſable obedience, <hi>omnibus licitis,</hi> in all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actions, to our Soveraign Lord the King, his Heirs and Succeſſors; not the leaſt tittle therein, though rack'd to a confeſſion by the moſt ingeniou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly-rebellious brain, giving them ſo much as a ſuppoſititious ground for their undertakings.</p>
            <p>And for the Law of God, How have they ſleighted it? the very Pulpits in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121190:13"/>many places, thundering out defiance to the morall obſervation thereof, declaring againſt his Majeſtie's defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Armes, and his loyall Subjects o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his juſt commands, with as much unbluſhing impudence, as the traiterous Preſſes did in their black lying Declarations; moſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly (the better to perſwade others to their rebellious aſſiſtance) ſtyling their rooting deſigne, <hi>The Cauſe of God</hi>— when as neither Old nor New Teſtament, Law nor Goſpell, Prophets nor Apoſtles, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially or circumſtantially, gave the leaſt warrant for ſuch a bloody and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Invitation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly— For I will rake no longer in this bloody puddle of Hypocriſie, but refer the Reader to the peruſall of all their Ordinances and Declarations, publiſhed, <hi>Anno</hi> 1641, 1642, 1643, 1644. containing aſſeverations and pretended proteſtations, to defend his Majeſtie's royall Perſon, Honour, Crown, and Dignity, the Proteſtant Religion, and the eſtabliſhed Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And turn my diſcourſive Pen in a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121190:14"/>more particular manner, by way of expoſtulation, to you Citizens of <hi>London</hi>— You, <hi>quos natura diligere jub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t; quamvis culpare ratio, religioque redar guere, imperat</hi>— You, whom naturall affection to your City com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth my affectionate pitty, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place, <hi>ubi primam vitalem hauſt auram;</hi> where I firſt ſtepp'd out of the dark, yet quiet, priſon of the womb, into this lighter and larger priſon of a world of miſeries: Although I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but blame you for your irregular, irreligious, rebellious, and bloody pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes againſt your Soveraign, and your own Native Country, ripping up the very bowells of your dear Mother with ſwords and ſpears. You, I mean, who have danced after the alluring Summons of theſe paper-Ordinances, or, if you will, abortive Laws; you, who have been ignorant-adherents (for ſo my charity ſtyleth you) to this root and branch rooting-faction, cheated into a forwardly aſſiſtance of their ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſigne, by thoſe ſpecious pretences formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>In a pretended proſecution of which, ſome years paſs'd, you Intrenched
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121190:14"/>your City, rais'd your Bulwarks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed both your time and eſtates, for the better ſecurity of your ſelves, and ſafety of your City, as relateth the Ordinance to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>But how, my dear Country-men,<note place="margin">Collectors. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> hath this been made good by you, or endeavoured by the contrivers of that Ordinance on your behalf?</p>
            <p>Did your mudd-walls ſecure your City againſt a domineering Army of your own raiſing and paying,<note place="margin">July 1647.</note> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon a violent entrance, if deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed conditionall admiſſion? when as ſome of your Citizens and others, paid too dearly for their forward, yet too late, reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tichburn. Wollasion. Fouk, Eaſtwick, Andrewes.</note>How was your City ſecured, when the Independent, rooting, factious Aldermen, and Common-councell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſprung out of the bowells of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Presbyterian-Rooters, betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you by ſo dull and ſtale a ſtratagem, as any, but ſuch Citizens, expresſing your ſelves witty in nothing but Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Rebellion, (as ſenſſeſſe, I think, as your earthy Bulwarks, though leſſe effectually powerfull for oppoſition) would have reſented and prevented.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121190:15"/>
            <p>What piece of treachery could be more obvious to any eye, eaſier to be read without ſpectacles, than that?</p>
            <p>The then-Presbyterian prevailing party within your City, and the <hi>two Houſes,</hi> unitingly declaiming againſt an inſolently-menacing Army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, rais'd by the wealth of the one, and authority, although unjuſt, of the other. The Presbyterian party, by their thundring Orders and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, commanding the Army's obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The Army again, not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying obedience to their commands, but commanding them to obey their particular contrary commands.</p>
            <p>Now amidſt this diſpute, obſerve, obſerve, you Cittizens, how ye were degreeingly cheated into the ſlavery of the Sword, by Creatures foſtered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your own wings.</p>
            <p>A Commanding Pack of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent factious Aldermen, and Common-Councell, with ſome few conjoyned Presbyterians, (who indeed like Ciphers were of no valew) muſt treat for a reconciliation, between the much abuſed City, and the abſurdly abuſing, and doubly died, rebellious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121190:15"/>Army, I mean the Independent facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Army. — A quaint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt! Was it ever known, that a known Thiefe ſat Judge upon the bench, to Condemne his fellow, complotting villany? I leave the application to each man's breaſt. O <hi>London, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don!</hi> how waſt thou then fool'd into what thou now art too ſenſible of, but then would'ſt nor believe, the reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Liberty and Honour? The inſolent Army the next day after this odde kind of reconciliation (or rather Confirmation of thy ſervitude) mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thorough thy ſtreets in Triumph forgetting thy formerly aſſiſting Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſcorning thee for thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Puſillanimous Condeſcention. And what accumulations of Taxes, Abuſes, Impriso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ments, Murders, have ſucceded this, <hi>ſcribere dolet;</hi> or rather, the thought of them grieveth me ſo much, that grief will not ſuffer me to mention them, but leave them to the Conſideration of the Citie's too too ſad experimentall knowledge.</p>
            <p>But I proceed— The Reſult of the hot Conteſtation of theſe * divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded dividers,<note place="margin">Fresh. Inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Concluded in this —
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121190:16"/>That the Power of Commanding in the <hi>Two houſes</hi> being at firſt, thus, (as you have read) peremptorily deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, was at laſt wreſted from them, by that Army whom they firſt gave onely power to act for them as ſervants, in proſecution of their firſt-reſolv'd upon Presbyterian deſigne— Where, by the way, I ſhall onely glance this Obſervation to the peruſuall of the moderatly-judging readers.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Members of the houſe Commons.</note>That thoſe perſons whoſe obedience would not ſtoop to the Juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their lawfull Soveraign, the King, though perſwaded and ingaged thereunto by the Law of God, the written Law of the Land; Oath upon Oath of Alleagiance, Supreamacy, and their owne Compoſed and injoyned Proteſtation, Knowingly, Cordially and Confeſſedly taken by them; are Commanded obedience to their own Creatures, and of Commanding Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters become Servants; nay Submiſſive Slaves to the imperious Propoſitions of their owne Created Servants.</p>
            <p>That they who in proſecution of an unchriſtian, unlawfull, bloody de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of taking away the power of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121190:16"/>King, juſtly by law and reaſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared His; of forcing away his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Voyce in a Lawfull Parliament, depriving him of the Command of the Militia; of bloodily changing the Civill and Eccleſiaſticall Goverment from Monarchicall to Ariſtocraticall, from Epiſcopall to Presbyterian. Witneſſe the tranſactions (to paſſe over other Treaties) of that too-late, tedious, and moſt unfortunate Treaty in the Iſle of Wight, in the managing whereof neither Law, Reaſon, nor Religion, urg'd by our dear Soveraign could work the Commiſſionated Treatours, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the factious Commiſſionating, Rooting Traytors in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> to Condeſcentions more than what ranne paralell and agreed with their moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt demands of all his Regall Power and wholly altering the government of his Kingdomes. Witneſſe alſo, the firſt inſiſted-on Propoſition; wherein, Good Prince, before they will proceed, He muſt, contrary to Reaſon, Religion, and Law, declaratorily Juſtify their unjuſt Actions of Rebellion and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt him, and Condemne his own Juſt defence as unjuſt.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121190:17"/>
            <p>The prevaling faction in the <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> ſtill upon Receipt of his Majeſty's Conceſſions and Anſwers to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Propoſitions,) Voting Not Satisfactory, Not Satisfactory (O fatall Word! <hi>Not</hi>) untill his Princely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Care of his Subjects (perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> Plotters.</note> Faction's reſolutions to perfect their bloudy deſigne) and his deſire of Peace, reconciliation, and ſtopping of that iſſue of blond by themſelves firſt made in his Kingdoms; at laſt (his own Royal Intereſt laid aſide) condeſcended ſo much to their demands that as a King he had nothing more to condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend unto, nor they more of his Regall Power to demand.</p>
            <p>Theſe men (who thus unlawfully proſecuted and perſecuted his Sacred Majeſty with diſtroying Armies, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt away his lawfull power upon Pretences of a Fundamental Law never heard of, never practiſed before in the Houſes, not ſo much as ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the leaſt imaginary authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Common Reaſon, much leſſe the law of the Land and the Proteſtant Religion, had all their bloudily acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red power. ſnatched from them by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121190:17"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Army.</note> thoſe I ſay, whom firſt they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered to offer bloudy force to his Majeſty upon grounds as ayry, groundleſſ, and unlawfull; as, pretences of Common Right, and diſtribution of Juſtice: as if Confuſion were that Right, and unparalelld injuſtice were the diſtribution of Common right and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">year </seg>1641</label> Some of theſe Ambitious and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Members, who by invited tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of the Citty-rabble forced his Majeſty, for the Security of his perſon, from his royall pallace at Whitehall, and ſoon after many of their then fellow-members, contrary to the Priviledge of all reaſonable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, were uncivilly forced out of the Houſe by their menaces and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring Votes, becauſe they would not be voting Conſpirators with them in their Trayterous deſignes, againſt their King, Country, &amp; the truly fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe, I ſay,<note place="margin">Parl.</note> were as abſurdly thruſt out of the Houſe by Pride and his Complices, the army's imps, birds of their owne hatching; inſtruments of their owne framing, upon accuſation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121190:18"/>of being fomenters of a New War, hinderers of Perfecting an intended Reformation, or, more truly, of Com-pleating a pre-reſolved reſolution, or rather a Jeſuitized independent deſigne ſomwhat more bloudy than the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Deus omnipotens in aetennum Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> Thy actions, O Lord, are all Juſtice, &amp; thy deeds Righteouſneſs it ſelf; Thou therefore, the fountain of all wiſdome, that doſt oftentimes proportion and ſymbolize, both for quality and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, mens puniſhments to their Sins; thereby, by plain demonſtrative ſignes, inviting them to repentance; — Grant, good Father, that all ſuch guilty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thus reading their iniquities in their puniſhment, may repent them of their fo mer Sins, that ſo thou mayſt pardon their tranſgreſſions and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their offences no more.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, reſtore, O Lord, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, the Purity of reaſon as men; A Zealous unmoved fixedneſſe in thy true religion the Chriſtian Proteſtant faith—; Loyalty and faithfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their undoubted Soveraign and Lawfull King, Cha.— the Second,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121190:18"/>&amp;c. and theſe not verbally, but really expreſſed by actions beſeeming men, whoſe reaſon not humorous opinion is their guide.</p>
            <p>By deeds befitting Chriſtian Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants whoſe<note n="*" place="margin">Scripture.</note> directing rule is the uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Word, &amp; not groundleſſe faincyed revelations, the Suggeſtions of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Angelicall Divell, and not the Perſwaſions of thee, who art the God of Spirits.</p>
            <p>By actions becoming Subjects, whoſe obedience without interruption willingly followeth the ſmooth Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of an Eſtabliſhed Law, not hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed along by the tumultuous Torrents of arbitrary Ordinances, nor Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entially ſwimming in the troubleſome Waters of mens Corupt wills. O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercyes, whatſoever puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Thou, in thy Juſt judgment, for our manifold ſinnes, ſhalt inflict upon us— give us not over to a generall infatuation of Spirit, a benummedneſſe in our Underſtanding and Reaſon, leſt we degenerating into the nature of beaſts with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> be deſign'd to graze in the feilds with beaſts that periſh.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121190:19"/>
            <p>O everliving God, Deprive us not of thy Candleſticke, thy goſpell of truth, leſt, for want of true guides, we all become blind; and, like them leading one another, irrecoverably fall into the Ditch of everlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>O Let not my Lord be angry, and thy Servant ſhall ſpeak but this Once.</p>
            <p>Father of Mercies, as we deſire that thy word may ſtill Continue a Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn to our feet, and thy Precepts a directing Light to our Paths; ſo we humbly beſeech thee, that out of thy infinit Loving kindneſſe thou wouldſt look upon us, and not take from us our Eſtabliſhed ancient, fundamentall Lawes; That ſo our Corrupt Natures may ſtill by them be rectified, the extravagant excurrences of our Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate perverſe Wills and actions may be limitted, leſt Ambition, Sedition, Treaſon, Perjury, Rebellion, Murder, Sacriledge, Regicidiſm, Envy, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Tyranny, Oppreſſion, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wickedneſſe, becoming particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Commanding Lawes, we, like Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Wolves, devour one another—
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121190:19"/>And, in order to this great mercy, good God, reſtore unto us our great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, Preſerver, and Protectour, thy Servant our Soveraign, the much wronged Princely Son of a more inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Murdered Martyr'd Royal Father, Cha — the Second, of Great Brittaine King &amp;c. Put the Sword and Scepter into his hands; Place the Crown upon his Head, Thou, who art able, and Powerfull in Extremities, in this his extremity ſhew thy Ability and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            <p>O Lord, as thou haſt deſigned him our Supream Governour; ſo, in order to his poſſeſſion of thine own deſigned Government, prepare the hearts of all his Subjects with ſubmisſive obedience unto him, as to thy Vice-gerent on earth; work into their ſpirits a ſenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their former erroneous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt his Royall father, and let their endeavours (for the reſtoration of his Princely ſon to his father's Throne) evidence to the world their unfeigned repentance for their ſins, committed againſt Thee the King of kings, in rebelling againſt their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraigne, contrary to thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121190:20"/>Law; the Law of Reaſon; and the eſtabliſhed Lawes of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What, Lord, although the furious Multitude, like the wild boares of the forreſt, have trode down the hedge of our Government, Our Lawes; and like rebellious Waves, with mad rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling actions, locally removed the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſupporting pillars of our Nation? Yet thou canſt in an inſtance fyle the teeth of the one, — and again raiſe up our defending and protecting Pales, with a word of thy Mouth; Canſt command back theſe furious Waves to their proper Center of obedience; and again, fixe our removed Pillars in their owne appointed place, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main like a rock immoveable; O Lord, Grant theſe petitions to thy poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervants, for thy Sonne Chriſt Jeſus ſake; O God of our Salvation, hear us: O thou, the hope of all the ends of the Earth, give us help againſt our trouble; for without Thee, vain is the help of Man —</p>
            <p>But to return to my former Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod —</p>
            <p>I could inlarge in ſuch kind of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary additions, and acquaint the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121190:20"/>World, how ſeverall others of the firſt practicall * rooting Faction,<note place="margin">Presbyt. Plotters.</note> have met with ſinne-ſpeaking Puniſhment, by the Practiſes of theſe ſecondugly Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; how like Pinns, though ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly rivetted for a ſetled Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſome Presbyterians have been knock'd out, and others cut off, onely to make way for more bloody Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent ſucceſſours; and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect could Patricularize ſome of all degrees, whoſe Lives, Reputations, or Eſtates, have been expoſed to the Block, Defamation, and Sequeſtration, by the Commands of theſe Monſtrous<note n="*" place="margin">Indep. Faction.</note> Tyrants, who from them received their firſt Power of Command. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, — &amp;c. the Pallace-yard, Blood-ſpeaking Scaffolds, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>But becauſe ſuch kind of diſcourſes may perchance, by the over-angry Judgement of ſome, be cenſured, as inclining to an uncharitable Upbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; (although my intent herein is onely like the Chirurgeon, who Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his wounded Patients, even to a diſpleaſed frown and angry Exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to prevent the feſtring of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121190:21"/>Wounds within, which would endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the whole body) thus, by ſuch ſharp lines to render the cure more certain, beyond doubt of Relapſe) I ſhall therefore ſilently paſſe over ſuch particular Perſons, not mentioning their Names at all; for I delight not in ſuch Repetitions; God, the ſearcher of hearts, knoweth that I write truth, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſhing all guilty Conſpiratours, and Frontiers, in this rebellion, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſuddain repentance, (it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſole deſign of this book) than the death, Ruine, or exemplary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any, either in Eſtates or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons —</p>
            <p>Thus I have laid before you the Religious vizards, the Pious Cheats of theſe rebellious Deſigners, and Complotting Rooters; in ſuch plain ſelfe-confeſſing and condemning De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, that every one that will not obſtinately cloſe the eye of his reaſon, cannot but confeſſe them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable truths —</p>
            <p>Having thus farre proceeded, and at this time being no leſſe confident, than charitable in my hopes, that all abuſed, miſleadd, formerly of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121190:21"/>Parry, are upon a penitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all return, I ſhall in the next place an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer an Objection, or rather ſhew the fallacy of a new-invented Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, much diſcourſed of by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Ruling Rule-leſs Independent Faction, and ſwallowed down with much eaſe by many, whoſe ignorance maketh them inſenſible of ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, or haſty-complying cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, altogether careleſſe of their Taſts— And it is this.</p>
            <p>That the preſent commanding Power exerciſe, <hi>Poteſtatem dominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi>— their governing, but more true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tyrannizing, power, over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> as having right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by Conqueſt, ſay they, having ſubdued them by the ſword.</p>
            <p>For the ſolution of which, it will be pains unneceſſary to meddle much with thoſe <hi>Argumenta Cardinalia,</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments <hi>primae magnitudinis,</hi> of the firſt ranck; at which their Plea of Conqueſt, at one touch (like aged tenants of the grave) would fall and moulder into aſhes.</p>
            <p>Therefore although I cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſilent, yet I ſhall be but brief in acquainting you,</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121190:22"/>
            <p>That it is againſt the principles of all Governments, for any Party what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, by force to endeavour an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of an eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, contrary to the fundamentall practice of that Nation.</p>
            <p>Now the fundamentall power of any Nation will appear thus.</p>
            <p>Where the power of making and repealing all kind of Laws, of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening and diſmiſſing Councills of Life and Death, &amp;c. are ſetled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and practically acknowledged; there is the fundamentall Power of a Nation.</p>
            <p>Now that this Power is ſetled in a free-Parliament, ſummoned by the King's command (without which, they could not aſſemble, and without whom,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>vide</hi> J.Jenkens</note> no new Lawes can be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, nor Old ones repealed, He being the ſole enlivener of all Law, and our ſupream Governour—) is a truth, which all the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and practiſed, do confirm.</p>
            <p>Again, that there is an indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neceſſity of maintaining this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, That all Governments muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main as they are eſtabliſhed, untill the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121190:22"/>fundamentally practiſed power of that Nation ſhall change the ſame, common reaſon will plead for me.</p>
            <p>For conſider — In all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there is an impowered Party Governing, and Perſons Governed— Now for the upholding and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Party, governing in ſecurity, to act accordingly, and whereby they may be enabled to preſerve their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons governed, in unity, peace, and concord; and for preventing the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious combinations of ſeditious and diſcontented perſons, from endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring any thing, that may tend to the diſturbance of the publick peace; that is, both the Power governing, and the Perſons governed— Laws are made, and thoſe alſo Penall, that ſuch diſturbers are no leſſe than Traitors and Rebells, againſt ſuch a Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Government—</p>
            <p>Witneſſe the good Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt all manner of Sedition,<note place="margin">J.Jenkens</note> Treaſon, and Rebellion. Nay, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thoſe baſtard-Laws of theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes, not that they deſerve the title of Laws; for Laws, rightly ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, are onely ſuch, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121190:23"/>their immediate direction from the Law of God, or elſe are Emanant from ſome circumſtantiall branch thereof, not any way ſtanding in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the ſubſtance of the Law Divine; that is, the Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and all Evangelicall Precepts; although ſuch Laws are made and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by men, as inſtruments. But theſe new-minted Laws are rather, <hi>Rapacitatis</hi> than <hi>Pacis,</hi> forced-up Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks to preſerve an unjuſt Power in tyranny and oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, you had the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> publiſhing the like, upon the Martyrdom of our dear Soveraign the King.</p>
            <p>Their Ordinances and Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, prohibiting all correſpondency with, and aſſiſtance of, his Royall Son, Now our Soveraign Lord and King.</p>
            <p>Their erection of that high Court of Ironicall Juſtice, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein.</p>
            <p>Their enjoyning of Subſcriptions to their <hi>Engagements.</hi> All which impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly contain ſuch a confeſſed Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Nay, were not this a truth eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to the fundamentall conſtitution
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121190:23"/>of a Government, as it is, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and maintained to be by all lawfull Powers; nay, made uſe of by Uſurpers themſelves; and the worſt of ſuch Uſurpers, <hi>Rebellious Subjects;</hi> and the bloudieſt of ſuch Rebells, thoſe who, exceeding their cruelty in the Goſpell, not onely abuſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, but have murdered the Lord of <hi>England's</hi> Vineyard,<note place="margin">Mark 12.</note> purſuing his Heir apparent even unto Reſolves of his death, that ſo the Inheritance may be ſolely in their poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>This, O God, thou haſt ſeen; O keep not ſilence, O Lord of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. Hide thy ſervant, our Soveraign, and all his loyall Subjects, from the conſpiracy of the wicked, and from the rage of theſe bloody men, that compaſſe them about with words of hatred, and fight againſt them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe.</p>
            <p>Were not, I ſay, this Principle granted, as it is by all Governments, it would out of neceſſity follow, that Maxims of Rebellion and Treaſon, were implicitely contained in ſuch a fundamentall conſtitution; not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, I ſay, that a Government
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121190:24"/>lawfully eſtabliſhed muſt ſo remain, untill alteration be made by the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame fundamentall Power which eſtabliſhed the ſame. Such a ſhadowy Government being like an Image, whoſe head's compos'd of gold, breaſt of ſilver, thighes of braſſe; but all this ſupported onely by leggs and feet of clay, eaſie to be uncontrolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly-ſhivered in pieces, by the leaſt malitiouſly-ſeditious and ambitious touch.</p>
            <p>Although I muſt confeſſe, that when ambitiouſly-ſeditious ſpirits complot the ruine of an eſtabliſhed Government; ſuch-like deſtructive tenents as theſe, of which I ſhall give an inſtance, practiſed by the rebellious Polititians of our daies, are divulged to deceive the common people, and invite then to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>As, that the <hi>two Houſes</hi> may aſſume a power, &amp;c. in caſe of the King's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in governing.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>two Houſes</hi> have power to diſpoſe of the Militia, in caſe the King conſent not, although it be to enable the One twentieth part of his Kingdom with power, to deſtroy the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121190:24"/>other Nineteen parts, Himſelf, and Royall poſterity.</p>
            <p>That the King muſt conſent to whatſoever the <hi>two Houſes</hi> ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, although never ſo irrationall, irreligious, and prejudiciall to Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and ſubjects.</p>
            <p>That, in caſe his Majeſty will not condeſcend thus, the <hi>two Houſes</hi> may exerciſe the Regall power, not onely without him, but againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pretty Principles indeed!</hi> equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to people governed, as to Kings and Governours ruling.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe it is true, that theſe, and ſuch like Tenents a theſe are, are not profeſſedly, nay, not ſo much as implicitely maintained by any Power whatſoever, either juſt or unjuſt; but are onely pretendedly divulged, I ſay, to catch the leſſe-knowing mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude into a Pecuniary and Souldiery aſſiſtance, the better to effect the ends of ſuch ambitious Deſigners.</p>
            <p>The truth of this being made good, and plainly appearing to every willing eye that will peruſe it, and unpreju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced judgment that will remain ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:121190:25"/>
            <p>Let us (with the eyes of our judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious memory, fixed upon what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready premiſed) lay the<note n="†" place="margin">Cr. Fact. Arm. Houſ.</note> preſent ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Power in one ſcale, and their Actions, Edicts, and Ordinances in another; and then judge, whether or no the actions of theſe worſt of men weigh not down their own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with a ſelf-condemning weight.</p>
            <p>For, that they have plotted, nay, effected, a forcible deſtruction of an eſtabliſhed Government, contrary to the Principles of all Governments, Law of God, Reaſon, and of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; ſwimming to their ends in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſtreams of Engliſh Chriſtian blood, untill at laſt they arrived at the deſtruction of our<note n="†" place="margin">C. R. I.</note> our Royall Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, is <hi>lachrymabile verum,</hi> too too ſad a truth, ſo appearing alſo by what I have already written.</p>
            <p>That the ſame <hi>ruling bloody power,</hi> ſince they have had the ſole power to Rule, have declared all thoſe to be Traitors and Rebells, in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, againſt them, who ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them in this their unjuſt poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the King's Majeſty's moſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121190:25"/>juſt Rights, and undeniable Power; their own Ordinances, or rather bloody Acts, confirm it true: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that cruell piece of cruelty, murdering maſſacre of thoſe Martyrs on earth, now glorious Saints in Heaven, Sir <hi>Charls Lucas,</hi> Sir <hi>George Liſle,</hi> the Lord <hi>Capell,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Hiae,</hi> Colonel <hi>Andrews,</hi> and ſeverall others; whoſe loyall actions onely endeavoured to relieve the oppreſſed, and reſtore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us our Religion, Laws, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, the ends of all juſt Wars.</p>
            <p>In brief, take both theſe together in this plain undeniable Syllogiſm.</p>
            <p>They are Rebells and Traitors, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to die an ignominious death upon the Gallows, (this is the ſenſe of their Ordinances, and finall reſult of their bloodily erected High Court) who ſhall diſturb the * <hi>Governours or Government of their Common-wealth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bloody Fact.</note> ſay they.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe very perſons</hi> have not onely diſturbed, but ruined the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of out Government, murdered the ſup ream Governour the King, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Kingdom and its Laws, by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121190:26"/>bloody Arms, Oppreſſion, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo, theſe are Rebells and Traitors,</hi> deſerving to die an ignominious death upon the gallows, by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, practiſes, and commands.</p>
            <p>Thus, <hi>Reos confitentes habetis; ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſua ipſorum verba, fiat Juſtitia.</hi> They plead guilty; may juſtice be done, according to their merits. Yet becauſe, <hi>non ſanguinis homo,</hi>— may they by repentance find mercy, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now conſider (my abuſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men); Where are the men, who ſtyle themſelves conquerors? Or, who can be ſo ſenſſeſſe, as well as heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, to tearm them ſo, when as, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the conſtruction of reaſon, they confeſſe themſelves to be but Rebells and Traitors?</p>
            <p>Indeed, many unjuſt Conqueſts there have been in the world, which truly were, as a prudent<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>K.</hi> James.</note> King ſtyleth them, but <hi>furta regalia, latrocinia ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſa,</hi> Royall robberies, occaſion'd by the boundleſſe ambitious ſpirits of ſome Princes, who many times have been repayed with the loſſe of their own Kingdoms. But did you ever read
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121190:26"/>or hear that rebellious Subjects, bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Traitors, mounted into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding power, by the miſ-employed wealth, and deceived aſſiſtance of their fellow Subjects, were ever ſtyled Conquerors over them?</p>
            <p>More plainly, for I would not have the people of <hi>England</hi> ſwallow ſuch groſſe abſurdities, ſuppoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of a juſt neceſſity ingaged to ſubſcribe to this unjuſt Power. Therefore,</p>
            <p>By way of a brief repetition, That there was at firſt a conſpiracy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of changing the Government of the three Kingdoms by force, if not willingly condeſcended unto by his late Majeſty,<note place="margin">Witneſſe 19 Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, <hi>cum reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis.</hi>
               </note> is ſo plain, that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt capacity cannot but condeſcend to it as truth.</p>
            <p>That this deſigne was veyled with ſpecious pretences, thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the judgments of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and create a military aſſiſting power, I have alſo made good.</p>
            <p>That, in common reaſon, without theſe pretences, it had been impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for theſe Conſpirators to have compaſſed their ends, any rationall
<pb facs="tcp:121190:27"/>man will, I am confident, confeſſe.</p>
            <p>For, Can any man beleeve that if theſe rooting-Plotters in the very beginning of this Fatall Parliament (for then it had the face of ſuch a Court) had decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the World their intentions, to extirpate Epiſcopacy; aboliſh the book of Common-Prayer alter the goverment of England; nay to Murder the King and Deſtroy his Royall off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring; infringe the liberties of their Perſons and Eſtates; burden them with Taxes upon taxes; and domineer onely by the Tyrannizing Sword; Can a man be ſo ſenſeleſſy Stupid as to Suppoſe that any one man in England would have contributed the leaſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance tending to ſuch deſtructive ends? — Surely not; Their Plotts had been as abortive-births, dead in the very womb; Like letters written on Sand, inviſible at the next windy blaſt; and themſelves had met with the reward of Traytors, in the Originall of their Treaſon.</p>
            <p>But I ſay, they muſt out of a Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick neceſſity by Pretences of a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation &amp;c. prepare the Common people for a Compliance, and upon
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121190:27"/>their deceived Compliance, hammer out by degrees their ugly Plot to a perfection.</p>
            <p>Away then with your moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous entitling God's approbation to your Succeeding Villanies; when as it is not Smiling Providence that waites upon your deſignes, as you would make the people beleeve, but the Graduall Effects of your politick Knaveries, and methodical Treaſons.</p>
            <p>Indeed, the All-juſt and wiſe God hath long ſuffered you to deceive the people of England, and them to be ſo deceived. But Gods deſigne thereby is to Chaſtiſe them for their inſtability, and diſobedience, in not valuing, or elſe lightly eſteeming the bleſſings of Peace; and puniſh them for their not prizing the Enjoyment of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Peace; and that you your ſelves by your additionall Sinnes, might be left inexcuſable at that great day of Account, when the Judg of Heaven and Earth ſhall pronounce that unrepealable doom, <hi>Ite Maledicti;</hi> Go, ye Curſed, into Everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>Again, to make this appear more
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121190:28"/>plain, take a further hint of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Method; which courſe had they not obſerv'd, they could have done nothing tending to the acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their deſigned Ends.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place they, though falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuggeſted into the Multitude's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leif, an alteration of our religion on his Majeſtie's part.</p>
            <p>And theſe ungrounded Pretences made way for Jealous and Suſpicious thoughts among the Common people: and theſe, though cauſſeſſe, Jealouſies occaſion the Multitude, conſtant in nothing but in Inconſtancy, to Stag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in their Sworn Alleagiance.</p>
            <p>In the next Place, following <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avells</hi> irreligious rule <hi>(Vehementer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepate et aliquid adhaerebit)</hi> they back them with lying invectives &amp; ray ling ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations againſt his Majeſty, &amp; his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Peaceable Juſt &amp; Merciful Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby the affections of many began to totter &amp; their dutie to ſhake, &amp; their needleſſe fears to encreaſe.</p>
            <p>Again, they Publickly cry'd up themſelves, though moſt untruly, as Aſſertours, Maintainers and Preſervers of our Religion) and the Lawes. And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121190:28"/>theſe falſe allures, attract the Aguiſh Judgments of too too many to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to them in their belief, and blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Obedience.</p>
            <p>Againe (the more to ingratiate themſelves with the Common People and hoodwinck them with Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that they were Perſons affecting Juſtice—) they Preſſe for Execution of Pretended Juſtice upon ſome Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Delinquents; who indeed were no other, but immoveable Loyall Rocks, hindering their Progreſſive Rebellious Plotts. And upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the incomparable Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and the unparallel'd Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> (two main ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting pillars of Church and State) were offered, as bloody ſacrifices, to the common people's ignorant zeal, and the conſpirator's deſignes.</p>
            <p>In the next place, they vilifie the honour of the King's perſon, adviſing the rabble of the City rudely to preſs into his Court, bawling for Juſtice, which never was denyed; and by this means, the reſpect and honour due to his Majeſty was weakened, the ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner'd people, following the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121190:29"/>counſell of their teachers, (apt ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their black mouth'd maſter the devill) began to revile the King, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Dominions, and ſpeak evill of Dignities.</p>
            <p>With theſe and ſuch like additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall inſolent deportments of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-ſcum, his wearied Majeſty was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, for his own ſafety, to leave <hi>London.</hi> After which, theſe rooting-Plotters perſecute him with dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Propoſitions, under the notion of Reformation, delivered moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly out of a Cannon's mouth; or mockingly tormenting him with<note n="*" place="margin">vid Collect Parl. Ord.</note> humble and loyall Petitions of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, preſented upon the point of a bloody Sword— Pretty Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects indeed!</p>
            <p>Thus, thus, <hi>England,</hi> thou waſt gull'd into a rebellious Army, to bring to paſſe their Conſpirator's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, upon the ſcore of thy own deſtruction, the loſſe of our peace, diſhonour of our Religion, ruine of the King's Majeſty, and the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This done,<note place="margin">Blaſphemy.</note> the Pulpit-Dragoons muſt intereſt the Deity in their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121190:29"/>Rebellion muſt be ſtyled, The Cauſe of God— O horrible blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my! as if the righteous and all-juſt God gave precepts, for the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the moſt unrighteous, unjuſt,<note place="margin">Caedem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um ad materiam ſuam.</note> and wicked actions that ever were committed. To this bad purpoſe, they cut and mangle, multiply and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, the holy Scriptures, wreſting them to a corrupt ſenſe, proper one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their deſignes, notwithſtanding that <hi>Anathema, Revel.</hi> 22. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18, 19, <hi>If any man ſhall add unto theſe things, God ſhall add unto him the plagues that are written in this book; and if any ſhall diminiſh the words of this prophecy, God hall take away his part out of the book of life.</hi> And by this means the poor people were ſeduced in matter of conſcience, obeying the politick Pulpit-directions, quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the commands of God, and their own former judgments and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes.</p>
            <p>All this while,<note place="margin">Lying. Diſſimu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the rooting Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers of State, were buſily buſied in abuſing the King, and cheating the people, ſenſleſly in their Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dividing the power of the King
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121190:30"/>from the King's perſon; as if there posſibly could be (in a true ſenſe) the exerciſe of a Kingly power, without the perſon of a King. But ſeaſonable it was for them ſo to do, when as they unjuſtly made uſe of power without, (nay, contrary to) his commands; and maintained Armies to fight againſt his Perſon.</p>
            <p>Next to this,<note place="margin">Perjury.</note> ſucceed new obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Oaths and Covenants, correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the ſenſe of their deſigne, and diſſonant from the legall, ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and religious ſenſe of all former lawfull Oaths; witneſſe their Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Oath, their firſt and ſecond Vow and Covenant, with their laſt and worſt, <hi>the Engagement;</hi> all which muſt be as chains to the people's conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, with which being once ſhack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, many of the Pulpits ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but a performance of theſe Oaths and Engagements, in the Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters deſtructive ſenſe; as if ſuch poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick State-Engines carried more truth in them, than the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Thus they made human policy Miſtreſſe of Divinity, nay, to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over her. Indeed, the Scots-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121190:30"/>as it was ſtyled, carried a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound ſenſe; in ſome Articles ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſeemingly-loyall and religious pretences; but they were but ſeeming ones; although in other, nothing but an enforced change of, both Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and Civill Government. Which, compared with precedent and ſubſequent actions, even untill his Majeſty was ſnatched away from the Presbyterian Power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſle</hi> Wight</note> maketh me grieve with admiration, and admire with grief, at many, who ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue adherents to thoſe firſt begun er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Principles, of extirpation of Governments by bloody force.</p>
            <p>Some affirming, ſtrangely and falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they did oppoſe the tyranny of the late martyr'd King, but never the Title or Office; which, to my mean apprehenſion, (and I could wiſh ſome of the Presbyterian party would otherwiſe inform my judgment) ſeemeth to oppugn reaſon it ſelf; his Majeſty having, before ever ſword was drawn, granted all things neceſſary to the well-beeing, quiet, and peaceable living of the loweſt, as well as the higheſt, of his Subjects,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121190:31"/>their poſſesſion on of their lives,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſſed by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> Collect. Parl. Ord</note> liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and eſtates, and a juſt reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Religion: He himſelf having raiſed ſuch Bulwarks for us to this purpoſe, that nothing was left for the people of <hi>England</hi> to deſire, as additionall to their future ſecurity and happineſſe. And had not this<note n="*" place="margin">Presb.</note> Kingly-power rooting-partie ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in, or, in their own irregular demands, been but modeſtly mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, theſe ſecond bloodieſt-rooting Independents had never comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly appeared to the world's eye, but <hi>England</hi> had ſtill remained the glory of Nations, an earthly Paradi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and not an habitation of Bats and Owles, Foxes and devouring Wolves; blind ignorance, hereſie, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hiſm, and Jeſuiticall bloody-minded men: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the former, and ſtill wilfully continuing Presbyterians, having nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon in Law, nor ground in Religion, for ſuch their a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, or ſtill continuing inoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations thereunto, as I have already made good— Maketh me to pray, that God would more clearly open
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121190:31"/>the Eyes of their underſtandings and in the bowells of Chriſt Jeſus deſire them that they would weigh all things by the ballance of the Sanctuary with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interjection of the leaſt part of a grain of Private Intereſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onate cleaving to Parties in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing unwarrantable by the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Standard of Gods word— and at laſt return from whence they were fallen, and do their firſt workes.</p>
            <p>But this by the way— However if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this I have diſpleaſed any man, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am Confident I have herein neither diſpleaſed nor diſhonoured the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth, &amp; therefore ſhall be bold to tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem that they do not well to be angry with me for ſpeaking the truth.</p>
            <p>I returne to my former Method—</p>
            <p>Why, thinke you, were ſo many Reverend Biſhops and other Orthodox Divines as Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> Dr. <hi>Oldſworth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Shute,</hi> with many others diſgraced or impriſoned; not becauſe the Law ſpake them guilty, but becauſe they were as ſo many walls of Braſſe able to Oppoſe their Proceedings; and would if ſuffered to Preach, have informed, the people their better duties and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121190:32"/>thereby prevented the progreſſe of their deſigues.—</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Garraway.</note>Why were ſo many Lords Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> ſome Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, outed and diſperſed unto Several Confining Caſtles —? Why were moſt of the Common Councell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefully thrown out of the Court? But only to make way for the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Spirits; who would more readily comply in their turnings &amp; windings with the firſt Moving Wheels of the Rooting-faction.</p>
            <p>Why did they then, and ſtill do, both admit and tolerate ignorant-Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to belch out new fangled falſe Opinions, Hereticall and Schiſmaticall poſitions? but thereby to bring the Clergy into diſhonour and diſreſpect with the people, diſtracting the brains and dividing the affections of the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: well knowing <hi>Machiavells</hi> rule <hi>divide et impera;</hi> for rebellion and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will never harbour in breaſts uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the bond of true religion: they that conſcientiously affect Chriſt and his Church, will not be wrought upon to deſtroy his Servants the Paſtours, or any Member thereof; nor ever give eare
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121190:32"/>to ſuch babblers, the Devill's Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines.—</p>
            <p>Nay their Preſent toleration of all in matters of religion;<note place="margin">Indep. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pretence of having a regard to tender Conſciences, is only done out of Policy, or, if you will, rebellious Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; not that they intend you (after that you have been inſtrumentall to their compaſſ'd Ends) ſuch a liberty out of a conſcientious Courteſy. But hear, hear, you deceived people of England! Their Reaſon is;</p>
            <p>Leſt the Ignorant Rabble (the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king inſtrumentall feet and active hands of their deſigne,) like your leſſe knowing Papiſts, taking all things by the hand of an implicit beliefe; ſhould, being denyed any one thing, grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a diſcontent, which (ſeconded with a Serious Repentance and its effects a deſertion of theſe Plotters, manifeſted by a generall inſurrection, their only fears) ſhould occaſion theſe Rooters ſuddain downfal &amp; utter deſtruction. For a diviſion in opinions and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at firſt rayſed them a Power ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling them to raze down Englands Monarchicall goverment; So a unity in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121190:33"/>iniquity; a Linck'd wicked brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood muſt ſettle them in this their deſtructive power. But, O Lord, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thy enemys have taken Crafty counſell againſt thy people, and have conſulted againſt thy Secret Ones; although they ſay, Come, let us cut them off from being a Nation, and let not the Name of a Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, King or people, be any more in Remembrance; Give not thou the Soule of thy Turtle dove unto the Beaſt and forget not the Congregation of thy Servants. Conſider thy Covenant; for many Places in England, Scotland and Ireland are full of the habitations of Cruell men. Judg the Cauſe of the fatherleſſe and oppreſſed; Ariſe, ariſe, O God, maintain thy owne Cauſe here, help and deliver us. So we thy People and ſheep of thy Paſture ſhall prayſe thee for evermore.</p>
            <p>Let us deſcend to examples of a Lower nature.</p>
            <p>Why, ſuppoſe you, is <hi>Lilly</hi> ſomuch imployed by theſe bloudy Statiſts? but onely to unhindg the faith of the common people from adhearing to the Doctrine of the holy Scriptures,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121190:33"/>which like a two-edged ſword, would ſoon cut their deſigne in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for, had the people's faith been kept to a cloſe dependence on the Word of God, and their actions one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regulated thereby; or, had<note n="*" place="margin">Presbyt.</note> others more knowing, or at leaſt pretending to more knowledge, weighed all their undertakings (without the addition of unbridled paſſion, and irregular, though ſeemingly zealous, affections) exactly, according to this everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſt Standard; ſo many formerly (now penitentiall men, I hope) had not then been deceived into a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Army; nor would ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their Adherents at this very day.</p>
            <p>But no wonder if thoſe men (who firſt rebell againſt the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and his Son, our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, fight againſt his commands, the practice of the whole Army of Martyrs the glorious company of the Apoſtles and Prophets, the example of the holy Church thorough the whole world) no wonder if ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and murder their Soveraign, God's Vice-gerent on earth, and all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121190:34"/>true Chriſtians, and faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. No wonder if ſuch men, having thus forſaken the fountain of living waters, (the Scriptures), do frame to themſelves new Ciſterns, even bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ciſterns of dependence on <hi>Lilly</hi>'s politick diſcourſes, which will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold water upon Scripture-try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all at preſent, nor be able to ſave or ſatisfie a poor ſoul at the great day of tryall, of particular perſons at the hour of death, or that generall Day of Judgment, when the world ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>But, let me deſire of all ſuch Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazers, and Star-believers, ſeriouſly to ponder that place of Scripture, in the 47<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> from the firſt verſe to the end, and lean no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon ſuch broken Reeds, which will deceive their dependence into a ſelf-deſtruction. <hi>Babylon</hi> there had truſted in the multitude of divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the great abundance of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters; ſaying to her ſelf, I am, and none elſe; I ſhall not ſit as a widow, neither ſhall I know the loſſe of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as <hi>the Rooters do.</hi> We are the onely Saints, we ſhall prevail. Upon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121190:34"/>no other ground, but their own ſtrength, and the truſt which they put in their proſperous wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now obſerve God's manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his judgments.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſaith the Text, verſe the 11<hi rend="sup">th:</hi> That is, becauſe you have thus ſinned, in punting confidence in theſe Star-gazers, and forſaken me the God of the Scars, and my unerring precepts, ſhall deſtruction come upon thee, and thou ſhalt not know the morning thereof; Ruine ſhall fall upon thee, which thou ſhalt not be able to put away; deſtruction ſhall come on thee ſuddainly unawares—</p>
            <p>Where, by the way, take notice, that as the Church's extremity is God's opportunity for deliverance, when their hearts are ſaddeſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed almoſt hopeleſſe, if they conſult onely with fleſh and blood; So, the deſtruction of the wicked ſhall come upon them, when they are at the higheſt of their hopes, and dream not of a change; then, even then, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, ſhall ſuddain deſtruction fall upon them— The Text ſaith, They ſhall not know the morning thereof;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121190:35"/>that is, not the time of their ruine: but after they have ſlept, as it were, a whoſe night in ſecurity, ſuppoſing all to be ſetled for a continuance, by the proſperity of their wickedneſſe; then ſhall God in the morning, unthought-of, unexpected, come againſt them in judgment, and deſtroy them in his fury.</p>
            <p>Further, in the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, upon their approaching ruine, obſerve, how God doth upbraid them with their ſins: Stand now among thy inchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and in the multitude of thy ſooth-ſayers, with whom thou haſt wearied thy ſelf, if ſo be thou maiſt have profit or ſtrength. Let the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, the Star-gazers, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. and Prognoſticators now ſtand up, and ſave thee from theſe things that ſhall come upon thee. That is, ſee if theſe your confidents can be a preſerving skreen between you and my deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing anger. No, no, hopes of help from them are but vain, for in-the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſes, ſee the judgment of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven denounced againſt the Star-gazers themſelves; Behold, ſaith the Text, they ſhall be as ſtubble, the fire ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121190:35"/>burn them, they ſhall not deliver their own lives from the power of the flame, &amp;c. Every one ſhall wander to his own quarter, none ſhall ſave them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall God ſay, Do you that adhere to the politick ſpirit of <hi>Lilly,</hi> and forſake the commands and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the God of ſpirits; even in that day, when you have filled full the meaſure of your ſins, when the Harveſt of your full-grown iniquities is ripe, then ſhall God enter in with his ſickle of judgment, and cut you off; and even then your conſciences ſhall upbraid you, and bid you go to <hi>Lilly,</hi> in whom you have truſted, ſee whether he can ſave you in that your extremity, try whether or no he can adminiſter the leaſt hopes of comfort to your ſouls for the future; but all in vain— O my brethren, there will be ſad thoughts at ſuch a time, and at the hour of death, when your ſouls are ready to take their flight from their fleſhy cages— Therefore conſider of theſe things betimes, before the hour-glaſſes of your lives are ſhivered into pieces. Repent and return, in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121190:36"/>your dependence onely upon the God of truth, and his revealed will, the holy Scriptures; leſt you exchange this life, for an eternally-continuing death, with thoſe never-dying damned in hell.</p>
            <p>To what end, think you, were, and ſtill are, your lying Pamphlets, and daily flying Diurnalls ſent abroad, but, like ſo many petty pieces of the ſame deceiving ſpirit, thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the poor people in a diſaffection to the King, and his ſo juſt a cauſe, and working of them into an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Conſpirator's deſignes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſting in them ſable lines of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, on the white innocence of his Majeſty's actions; and covering over the rotten wall of their own black undertakings, with a ſeeming white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe witneſſe that apoſtatizing<note place="margin">Politicus, alias Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
               <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer,</hi> fallen from the heaven-appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heighth of truth and loyalty, to the deepeſt hell of perjury, falſhood, rebellion, and treaſon; whoſe lines are nothing elſe but lying invectives, murderers of Religion and Reaſon, as well as of Royalty and Loyalty.</p>
            <p>What, ſuppoſe you, my abuſed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121190:36"/>country-men, is the reaſon why the Conſpirators endeavours tug ſo much to engage all, if it were poſſible, to be equally guilty with them, ſome by perjurious oaths and engagements; others, by ſacrilegious barterings for the Churches Lands; ſome, by unjuſt poſſeſſion of his Maleſty's Revenues and Royall Eſtate, with the Lands of his loyall Subjects; and not a few <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Accuſer of Col. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> exchanging their ſouls with the devill by apoſtacy and treachery, for a pecuniary reward.</p>
            <p>It is onely that they may be as <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſi proditione,</hi> ſo <hi>form doloſi numero;</hi> that their number may ſeem terrible; and what they cannot maintain as juſt by Reaſon, Religion, or Law, they may ſeem to juſtifie the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof by the irreligious Sword. But do thou, O Lord God of Hoſts, ſcatter thoſe people that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in war, that ſpeak not peace, but deviſe deceitfull matters againſt the quiet of the land—. They ſmite down thy people, O God, and trouble thine heritage; they ſlay the widow and the ſtranger, and murder the fatherleſſe. O Lord God the avenger, O God the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121190:37"/>avenger, ſhew thy ſelf clearly. Lord, how long, how long, Lord, ſhall the wicked triumph, and the workers of iniquity vaunt themſelves?—</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall contract all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a narrow compaſſe; and, as I have already made it appear,<note place="margin">Indep. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> that the * pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ruling Powers are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entitled Conquerors, that they have confeſſed themſelves to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells and Traitors; ſo all others ſhall affirm them (as to be ſuch, ſo alſo) the bloodieſt of Cheaters, and State-jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall do, firſt, by inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſad modern ſtory, and then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a comparative notice of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties employed, with the end of their then employment, and theſe Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-cheaters, who would be ſtyled Conquerors.</p>
            <p>I have been informed, that in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> at the firſt ariſe of that bloody Rebellion, there were ſome of the Papiſticall faction reſolved upon the ſurpriſall of a Proteſtant Juſtice of Peace, (where, by the way, take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that ſome of his ſervants were privy to the conſpiracy), the death of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121190:37"/>him, ruine of his family, and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Caſtle. But they ſuppoſing it in vain to attempt it by force, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon a more ſubtle way, (by putting on the vizor of Juſtice, and of former Acquaintance, upon their deceitfull intentions) thereby to compaſſe their ends; in this manner.</p>
            <p>The Combinators bind the hands of ſome of their fellow-villains, take with them a Conſtable and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, inſenſible of the plot; knock at the Caſtle-gate, pretend they came for juſtice againſt theſe bound men. Some of the ſervants, as well of the combination, as others that were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their deſigne (however, being both acquainted with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, and many of the reſt) admit them into the preſence of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Which was no ſooner done, but, after ſome pretended flouriſhes for juſtice, they unbind their fellow-vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, and all unanimouſly murder the Juſtice, his family, faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and the well-meaning Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and keep poſſeſſion of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</p>
            <p>Now let any rationall man reſolve
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121190:38"/>me. Do theſe men deſerve to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as reall Landlords, when as, had they not thus pretended juſtice, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by even deceiving the <hi>Juſtice</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, it had been impoſſible for them to have effected their deſignes? Or will you not rather confeſſe, that they were the worſt of deceivers, and bloodieſt of murderers? Or can any man be ſo ſenſleſſe to affirm, that, becauſe they were actually poſſeſt of this Caſtle, their poſſeſſion therefore was juſt? Surely no. Or if any after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall combine with theſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, in this Caſtle ſo unjuſtly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, will not all rationall men judge them equally guilty? Certainly yes.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>mutatis nominibus de Anglia fabula narratur.</hi> To make good the compariſon.</p>
            <p>Who are theſe Papiſticall bloody Conſpirators, but the Rooting-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (though different in title) in the Houſe and Army?</p>
            <p>Who this Proteſtant <hi>Juſtice</hi> of Peace, and faithfull ſervants? but our late dear Soveraign, and loy all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whom they have murdered? and the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> which they have deſtroyed?</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121190:38"/>
            <p>Who thoſe ignorantly aſſiſting Conſtables and Officers? but the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead deceived Presbyterian party— miſlead, I ſay, for there were plotters among them too, (whom, in this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntend not.)</p>
            <p>Who are thoſe treacherous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants?<note place="margin">Mildmay. Vanes.</note> but thoſe of his Majeſty's own houſhold. What is meant by this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle? but the three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>How and by what means poſſeſſed, which otherwiſe could not have been obtained? but under pretences of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Juſtice. Now for the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the act, I leave to every man's nearer application; onely know thus much for truth,— That proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous villany entitleth nothing to be therefore juſt and equitable, becauſe ſucceſsfull. What though<note n="*" place="margin">As two Fryers tearmed the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the French King, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, &amp; donum Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>proſperum ſcelus Virtus vo catur,</hi> yet really it is not ſo; it is but the corrupt gloſſe of wicked men, and bloody Tyrants, who would ſeem to have power to dethrone the Majeſty of Religions Reaſon in man, as ſome have had to deſtroy Kings and Governments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thus, thus, <hi>England,</hi> theſe Roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121190:39"/>factious <hi>Conſpirators</hi> have (<hi>grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> ſtep by ſtep) juggled themſelves into a Supremacy, and abuſed you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſlaviſh ſubjection.</p>
            <p>By this time, I preſume, all are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in theſe <hi>Men's</hi> deſerving titles: and let them receive their due cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The unparallel'd Impoſtours.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Unheard of State-cheaters.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bloodieſt of Rebellious Tyrannicall Subjects,</hi> but not Conquerors.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now let me appeal to all Engliſh hearts, and true-hearted Proteſtants:</p>
            <p>What ingenious ſpirit will not bluſh, after he apprehendeth himſelf to be conſened by the cunning inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations and actions of any men, though in matters of leſſer conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence?</p>
            <p>What repairings are there to the Lawyers for advice?</p>
            <p>What earneſt endeavours are there employed, either for a Reſtitution or Vindication. To this purpoſe, no means are left unattempted, no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unexpended, no friends neglected, or un-made uſe of, that may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to ſuch an end.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121190:39"/>
            <p>And will you, you Engliſh-men, being thus cheated, not of toyes and trifles, but of things ſubſtantiall and eſſentiall, both to your temporall and eternall welfares. Your King, the Supream Governour being murdered, and his Royall Son, our ſurviving So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Perſecuted, proſecuted with murdering Reſolutions, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Armies. Your Laws, they being aboliſhed; your Religion, that being diſhonoured and corrupted with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Schiſm, and all manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane opinions; your Liberties and Lives, they lying at the beck, and command of theſe cheating Tyrants: Will you continue further inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to the abſolute deſtruction of all theſe, wherein you are concerned as Chriſtians, and free-born Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? Will you ſubſcribe your ſelves willingly paſſive ſlaves to theſe active impoſtors? Nay, will you engage your ſelves in obedientiall<note n="*" place="margin">Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> promiſes to ſuch an unjuſt power, enchaining thereby your ſouls to their monſtrous ſins;<note place="margin">Quos ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les culpa coinquinat par quoque paena con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringet.</note> and, unleſſe repentance prevent, linking your ſelves to their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? For God will be juſt.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:121190:40"/>
            <p>Let me perſwade you therefore, my dear brethren and Country-men, in the bowells of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt, as you tender your eternall welfare and everlaſting happineſſe, not to be yoked together with theſe perfidious creatures; for, what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe? what commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion hath light with darkneſſe? what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? what agreement hath innocent loyalty with bloodily guilty perjury? Separate your ſelves from their wicked acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, come out from among them, be no longer partakers of their Sinns leaſt you receive of their plagues.</p>
            <p>Now at the laſt ſtand faſt in the faith, quit yourſelves like men and beſtrong, withſtand the Devill and he will fly.<note place="margin">Ille Chriſti miles qui pugnat, non qui fugit.</note> It is your Puſillanimity and Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cowardice that ſpirits theſe Rooters to a progreſſion in their ugly defignes — By this only they Worke,</p>
            <p>Do you ever hope to be freemen again, Free by vertue of a Certainly Protecting and directing Law, ſo Long as you are poſſeſſed with ſuch aguiſh
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121190:40"/>ſpirits? No no, be aſſured while you retaine this Puny ſpiritedneſs, expect nothing but a multiplication of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive Taxes, like waves upon the Sea ſhore, tumbling one upon the neck of another, untill you be all over whelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with irrecoverable poverty. Away then with this ſlaviſh fear; why will you rather ſubſcribe to be Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſinne with theſe men, than to be Champions for the true cauſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the Lawes of England and your owne liberties. Let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to throw away theſe dull weights, which like Plummets tyed to the feet of flying birds, preſſe down your winged deſires of Reſtoration and rein joyment of Peace and Truth. It is theſe Plummets of feare that more keep you under hatches of ſlavery than their often reiterated tyrannicall oppreſſion.—</p>
            <p>Indeed it is true that a generall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poveriſhment of all degrees of men (but thoſe of their lincked conſpiracy) is the high rode of Policy on their parts. For by this the oppreſſed (mens ſpirits many times declining with their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates) in continuance of time are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121190:41"/>of meanes to obtain their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and at laſt through meer neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity enforced, contrary to their owne reaſon and conſciences, to enroll them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as Souldiers in a Rebellious army.—</p>
            <p>But ſhall They be ſo Politick as firſt to work us into a neceſſitous condition, and then work upon that neceſſity, their owne ends, in our Ruine? and ſhall not We (ſeeing our ſelves thus driven into a pitt of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction) endeavour ſomuch as to ſtruggle for our owne Security and prevention of our enforced ruine—? Nay, ſhall we become aſſiſtants to the deſtruction of our remaining loyall fellow Subjects, who by ſuch cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice have our ſelves only occaſioned our owne Ruine—? O Stupid genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of people, who have bewitched us! Heare oh <hi>England,</hi> and O <hi>London</hi> harken; now at laſt return, return, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, to the God of heaven by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for thy often repeated Sinns to your Soveraigne and the Lawes of England, by a willing and Reall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to your fellow country men in mutuall embraces of unity and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall affections.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121190:41"/>
            <p>But, me-thinks I hear ſome whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering a commendation of the Plotters charity; that, notwithſtanding they have reduced many into an impover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed condition, yet they are carefull in making proviſion for them in Now erected Hoſpitalls.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, Let me tel you this truth: that their care it expreſſ'd to none but ſuch who firſt have cripled their ſouls as well as maimed their bodies in their bloudy deſigne (ſtrange dealing to cut off mens legs purpoſly to ſhewtheir charity in the guift of a paire of crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches!)</p>
            <p>But grant their care were more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and extended to others, whom their cruelty, plunderings, taxes and neceſſary expences only to buy bread (wanting Suplies through the want of Trade, their only way of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, loſt by their Rebellious warrs) had reduced to Extreamity of Poverty.</p>
            <p>All though this, I am confident, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from any principle of Chriſtian charity neither, but pure po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy; thereby to lull aſleep the cryes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121190:42"/>of the maymed, the Widdows, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe; which if too publikly heard, might occaſion others to be fearfull, how they become either actively or paſſively contributary to their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, from whom they can after all expect nothing but to be Famiſhed for a Reward.</p>
            <p>Yet alas, poor <hi>England,</hi> muſt thou be firſt beggered by theſe Plotters, that they may expreſſe a cruell kind of charity to thy miſery, by them only occaſioned? Miſerable Charity ſure! To Robbe and Spoyl men of their own Eſtates that they, their wives, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, may become Penſioners in an Hoſpitall.—</p>
            <p>But I Proceed.</p>
            <p>Having thus layed down, the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Juſtice on his Majeſtie's part, the Rebellious method and Trayter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous means which theſe Conſpiratours have made uſe of, as ſo many aſcending ſtepps aſſiſting the accompliſhment of their bloudy deſigne, hoping that all rationall men are very well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied how they have been abuſed by theſe deceivers into the commiſſion of unlawfull actions, and are reſolved
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121190:42"/>for a Serious repentance and Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain amendment, that ſo the God of heaven may Reſtore unto us our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne on his throne; Our religion to its Practicall Purity; and our ſelves to the enjoyment of our Lawes and Liberties:</p>
            <p>I ſhall in the next place, acquaint the world with the unlawfullneſſe of that Politick piece of Combinatory villany <hi>(the Engagement),</hi> that trod upon the heels of other preceding actions, in order to their deſigne; as naturally as the ſhaddow of man, on a ſunny day, waiteth upon the body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">January 1648.</note>To this Purpoſe therfore take notice that after they had Murdered the King in their rode of Bloudy policy, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately Iſſued forth firſt that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy-diſtroying Ordinance, and an utter extirpation of his Majeſtie's Royall family, not ſo much as mentioned in any of their preceding Declarations— Nor indeed was it ſeaſonable they ſhould — But when they had runne through all their Scenes of Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Pretences of ſetting up of Chriſt Jeſus, though Murdering again thereby the Lord of life by their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold ſins; at laſt moſt Barbarouſly they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121190:43"/>killed the Lord's Anoynted, the King: He muſt have his bloody <hi>Exit</hi> out of this world, to make way for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon the bloodied ſtage of his Kingdoms, there to act their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing parts of deſtruction upon the Royall Perſons of his Poſterity, and to contrive the ruine of all loyall and faithfull Subjects, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And now having brought them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (their firſt reſolved end, thorough all their vain turnings, and politick windings); Take a view, how they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſettle themſelves in their bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily-acquired Power, endeavouring to lock others in an unjuſt obedience unto them, by commanding ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to that complication of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Rebellion, <hi>the Engagement,</hi> and by theſe commands to diſtinguiſh affection, that ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Rooters.</note> they may more readily make way for the ruine of all true Chriſtians, in their perſons and eſtates, thereby to require thoſe of their more near and bloody faction; as alſo, that ſuch, and none but ſuch, moſt deſperate villains, may be inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in all employments, both in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121190:43"/>Church and State. Thus much may be collected very eaſily, by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves of the Parliament (ſay they; but traitorous Conſpirators, ſay I) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning ſubſcription thereunto, Yet,<note place="margin">Oct. 1649</note> by the way, let me tell them, that though hereby they ſeem to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh perſons, yet their hearts and ſouls they cannot— Alas, this ſeeming Tye— although for my own part, I diſapprove the ſubſcription of any one whomſoever, becauſe hereby, men ſeem more to fear Man than God, love their golden earth, a little periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wealth, more than the rich treaſurs that are laid up in Heaven, for thoſe that fight the good fight of faith, and perſevere unto the end, to whom one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Crowns of everlaſting glory are promiſed as rewards. I am afraid,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugitius nulla Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> that their ſins of ſubſcription will occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the continuance of our puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; although, ſay I, this Tye, in reference to the perſons obliged unto, will prove but like ſandy ropes, which the alteration of the wind will ſoon ſcatter into nothing.</p>
            <p>Before I come to diſſect the Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf, and lay it open to the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121190:44"/>world's eye, that ſo all that will, or are not as yet given over to a reprobate ſenſe, may therein read the preſent ſin, and future everlaſting danger (without repentance) of the ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>I muſt, by way of repetition, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe theſe confeſſed, and already-maintained principles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>vid.</hi> Judg. Jenkins's <hi>Collect.</hi>
               </note>That the King's Majeſty, now <hi>Charls</hi> the ſecond, by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall law of <hi>England,</hi> is our Supream Governour.</p>
            <p>That, as this his Supremacy is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated in our Laws, ſo the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment thereof is imbodied in our Religion, (the true Chriſtian Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant faith) maintained in the XXXIX Doctrinall Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and this conſonant to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>That this acknowledgment is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Precept, Practice, Oath upon Oath of Allegiance and Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, was a truth confeſſed by all Engliſh Proteſtants, untill theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, wherein theſe bloody and ſeditious ſeeds (like thoſe tares in the Goſpell, ſowen in the night while
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121190:44"/>others ſlept) are ſcattered abroad, as it were, in the night alſo, by theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh inſtruments, when all Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Miniſters were forced either to ſilence, or elſe caſt into dark priſons, like ſo many ſhining Suns, by them forced under clowds, the great reaſon of this our preſent night of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and helliſh errours. However, this truth ſtill remaineth (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo many bloody ſtorms, and rebelliouſly oppoſing waves) like a Rock unſhaken, being built, not on ſandy foundations, but on ſure Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of undenyable Reaſon, pure undefiled Religion, and Laws, like Rivers from their fountains ſtreaming forth, and remaining apparently eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed at this very day;</p>
            <p>That a bloody and enforced extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of a Government by Subjects, contrary to the power, &amp; commands, and againſt the Perſon of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraigne, and the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Law of the Kingdom, is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of Treaſon and Rebellion, by their own confeſſion.</p>
            <p>That ſuch practiſes are againſt the principles of all Governments, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121190:45"/>condemnable by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>From all which confeſſed Poſitions, we may collect this Truth in generall,</p>
            <p>That in reference to the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of powers by Law, Reaſon, and Religion (the Touchſtone of all Powers, that is, Governments, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever) maintained juſt, ſuch as the King's Supremacy and Regall Power is, no obedience active ought to be rendred to Powers, or rather Perſons unjuſtly uſurping a Power, ſuch as theſe rooting-Conſpirators are, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving neither warrant by Religion nor Law to command ſuch an oppoſing obedience, much leſſe to do as they have done, <hi>viz.</hi> to murder and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne Kings, ſubvert our Religion and Laws, endeavouring to vaſſalize us to a ſubmiſſion unto their unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full commands. For it is better to obey God than man; that is, when our refuſall of obedience to mans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull commands, are warrantable by his all-commanding Law—</p>
            <p>But let us examine the Scripture. Every ſoul muſt be ſubject unto the higher power,<note place="margin">Rom. 13</note> ſaith the Scripture, that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121190:45"/>is,<note place="margin">There is no power but of God, if they be godly powers. Bad Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are by the permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not the ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God.</note> thoſe juſt Powers whom God hath ordained for the good government of his people, and have right and title to be ſtyled Governours, being regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received, ſetled, practiſed, and confirmed in a Nation, as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>England</hi> was by King, Lords, and Commons, all acting or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in their ſeverall Sphears, yet all meeting in an unanimous agreement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the generall good both of Prince and People. And theſe thus meeting and conſulting together, the High Court is rightly entituled a PARLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AMENT, a name in it ſelf venerable, and to be greatly eſteemed by all true Chriſtian hearts. Such a PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, O God of mercies, reſtore unto poor decaying and dying <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Now that this command of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection muſt concern onely the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full governing Power, and not rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subjects, who, by treachery, blood, and deceit, have ſnatched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the power of governing from the lawfull Governours, and exerciſe it by a ryrannicall uſurpation, both o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Prince and People, the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent words of the Text confirmeth.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:121190:46"/>
            <p>For, to what end were that advice of the Apoſtle, That Princes are not to be feared for good works, but for evill? That is, if people governed be obedient, and act in their places things unblamable, the Prince and the Law need not to be feared by them, in a way of condemnation and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But if Subjects (to ſpeak in the words of the Apoſtle) ſhall do evill, by infringing the Law of God, by rebelling againſt the lawfull Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Governour, <hi>(as this prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling faction hath done)</hi> then the Prince, he bearth not the ſword in vain, for he is the Miniſter of God to take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on ſuch evill doers, that is, to puniſh them according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits.</p>
            <p>Now do I wonder, how any man can be ſo unbluſhingly impudent,<note place="margin">needham <hi>Politicus.</hi>
               </note> as to make uſe of this Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly to engage the common people of <hi>England</hi>'s ſubjection to this preſent <hi>Rule-leſſe Ruling Power,</hi> when as on the contrary they are hereby obliged to be aſſiſting to their Prince, that ſo he may be the better enabled
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121190:46"/>to diſcharge that duty, which God and the Law requireth from him, and to puniſh theſe workers of iniquity. The current of the Text running clearly for ſubjection to lawfull Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, from the people who are to be governed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nullius prohibitio valet divinis obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e praeceptis,</hi> Gods precepts may not be countermanded by man's prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions; nor God's prohibitions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced by man's precepts.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.</note> we are exhorted to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelves to every Ordinance (that is, lawfull Ordinance) of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King, as to the ſuperiour, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Governours, as unto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of evill doers, and the praiſe of them that do well. Where, pray take notice, the Apoſtle's advice is quite oppoſite to the practice, either of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator's, or the ſubjecting Subſcribers of theſe daies; for we are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſubmit our ſelves to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wicked Ordinance, by which good men are onely injured, and the worſt of men commended; nor are we to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121190:47"/>obey the now<note n="†" place="margin">The King being Supream in his own Kingdom, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can be but Subjects; and if Subjects have no power to command, but by way of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation from the King, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the preſent ruling Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction have no juſt power to command, but fall under the notion of wicked and evill doers, whom the King ought to puniſh, and all good men ſhould be aſſiſting thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to— This is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtle.</note> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering Power, (but the King as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream) therefore not theſe who are but Subjects, nor any of their Agents, whoſe commands and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons already have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the King, our Supream Governour, and ſtill continue to deſtroy his Royall Son, and all others, who will not walk in the ſame bloody paths with them. Is this, think you, to ſubmit to the King as Supream? In brief, the Scripture enjoyneth us to obey the King and his ſervants; The Faction commandeth us to obey them (ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) againſt the Kings commands de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Him and all his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>O monſtrum, horrendum</hi>—<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Are theſe the good works which the Apoſtle commandeth us to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe of the ſame Chapter, that God may be glorified by us in the day of viſitation? And is this our honeſt converſation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121190:47"/>we may ſtop the mouth of evill ſpeakers? Surely no, my dear Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, It were blaſphemy onely to ſuppoſe ſo.</p>
            <p>Is the wilfull ſleighting and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting of God's precepts, and the dethroning of Kings, the way to obey God and honour the King, as we are commanded in the ſame Chapter?</p>
            <p>Did our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,<note place="margin">Matth. Mar.</note> that thoſe things which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould be given unto him, and ſhall the Faction not onely command the contrary, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves plunder all from him, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him of his Honour, Regality, Revenues, nay, Life and all?</p>
            <p>Shall the Preacher advertiſe us to obey the Kings commands,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.</note> in regard of our Oaths; and ſhall the Faction command us to diſobey his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands? nay, engage us by contrary Oaths, thereby making us guilty of a double perjury?</p>
            <p>Nay, ſhall the people of <hi>England,</hi> upon, as it were, the firſt invitation of theſe Conſpirators, ruſh into the ſin, and yet think to eſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Surely no. Though God be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121190:48"/>mercifull, yet he is alſo juſt. Read the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> from the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe to the end of the Chapter; there ſee how God denounceth his wofull judgment againſt perjury; and repent before it is too late.</p>
            <p>Shall the Wiſe man adviſe us,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.</note> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King there is no riſing up?</p>
            <p>Shall the Faction perſwade us that for the Kings protection there muſt be no riſing at all?</p>
            <p>Muſt not we curſe the King in our hearts?<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10</note> and nevertheleſſe do theſe Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him with their bloudy hands? nay, put him to variety of death with their Pens and Tongues ſharper than two edged Swords.</p>
            <p>Shall the Apoſtle exhort, that firſt of all Supplication &amp; Prayers be made for Kings &amp;c. And ſhall the Prayer-haters, though pretended affecters, command us not to pray for the King at all? Nay ſhall we obedientially comply with theſe Scripture-murderers; aſwell as King Religion and Law-deſtroyers?</p>
            <p>Although the Scripture acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us,<note place="margin">Prov. 24.</note> that he which provoketh the King to anger ſinneth againſt his own Soul;— Yet theſe Conſpiratours think it no Sin to imbrue their hands
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121190:48"/>in the bloud of Kings.—O my God, conſider how theſe men of bloud blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thy Name; ſinning with an high hand againſt thee, the all-powerful Lord of heaven and earth, contrary to the Precept and Practiſe of thy Son Chriſt Jeſus, thy holy Prophets, and Apoſtles. But, O my ſoul, partake not thou of their counſells, nor follow thou their rebellious ſteps.</p>
            <p>By this time I preſume it will be granted,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.6.</note> that we muſt ſubmit to all lawfull powers, yielding ready obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto them in all things that are lawfull; but muſt not ſubject our ſelves in an active obedience to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unlawfull, <hi>(ſuch as theſe Rooters are)</hi> by way of oppoſition to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's lawfull and Scripture-appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Supremacy. So that, in brief,<note place="margin">Fact. Indep</note> * Theſe being neither lawfull Powers, nor commanding lawfull Acts, muſt not be obeyed, unleſſe we reſolve to ſin againſt the light of Reaſon, the Law of God, and all Evangelical Precepts.</p>
            <p>Now, by the way, let me deſire all you Subſcribers to the <hi>Engagement,</hi> ſeriouſly to read and conſider what you have done, (not that I ſay, you are obliged thereby to any perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121190:49"/>for, <hi>contra Scripturas nulla ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatio,</hi> the Scriptures engage you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a repentance.) However, take notice, how you have frolick'd away the innocence and integrity of your conſcience, ſinning againſt the God of heaven.</p>
            <p>Let ſuch alſo weight theſe things in the ſcale of the Sanctuary, forbearing addition of one grain of their ſelf-by-aſs'd ends, or private corrupt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, who fooliſhly ſooth up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their vain conceit, that the <hi>Engagement</hi> is but a civill thing, and not in a religious ſenſe to be taken notice of. That any man may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, and accordingly expreſſe an active obedience to theſe Rooters, during the time of their command; and when another Power ſucceedeth this, be obedient to that likewiſe. A pretty ſort of earthly Chriſtians! for aſſuredly heaven nor heavenly things theſe mind not. What? Is perjury no ſin? Is not a combination to deſtroy your Religion, your King, the widow, fatherleſſe, your fellow-ſubjects, no ſin? Do you make it but a kind of a complement thus to ſerve the devill, who hath been a murderer and a liar
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121190:49"/>from the beginning? See,<note place="margin">Joh.8.44.</note> my friendly Country-men, with what glaſſy cords you bind up your eternall happineſſe? on what icie bridges you adventure the everlaſting welfare of your ſouls?</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I ſhall unravell this bloody-twiſted piece of Perjury, Murder, Rebellion,<note place="margin">Engagem.</note> and Treaſon, as it is intentionally meant by the Compoſers, although I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, not ſo reſolvedly taken by moſt of the Subſcribers; although, let them alſo wreſt or mince the ſenſe as they pleaſe, they cannot excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the guilt of ſin in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall preſent it you in groſſe. <hi>I do declare and promiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">October, 1649.</note> 
               <hi>that I will be faithfull to the Common-wealth of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>as the ſame is now eſtabliſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King or Houſe of Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ſhall give it you in its ſeverall pieces; and, with them, a rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall expoſition of their moſt irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, irreligious, intentions therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I— that is,</hi> I, a ſubject bound by the Law of<note n="*" place="margin">1. Pet. 2. Rom. 12.1 Eccleſ 8. <hi>vid.</hi> J. Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections.</hi>
               </note> God and † Man, and by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall additionall<note n="*" place="margin">Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Oaths, to be true and faithfull to my Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charls,</hi> his Hairs and Succeſſors,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121190:50"/>the Kings and Queens of <hi>England;</hi> to be aiding to Him in my life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune againſt all Rebells and Traitors whomſoever;<note place="margin">11th. <hi>Hen.</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. cap. 1.</note> to diſcloſe all conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies againſt his Perſon, Honour, Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>I being thus conſcientiouſly, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, and legally pre-ingaged; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, <hi>I do declare and promiſe, that I will be true and faithfull;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that is, faithfully true in my obedience and ſubjection, <hi>to the Common-wealth,</hi> (but more truly, common-Woe-creating Rooters) that is, <hi>To an inconſiderable number of bloody perjur'd Traitors, ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious, ſacrilegious perſons, congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> (contrary to all Law, Reaſon, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Equity) <hi>and met together un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſalſ veil of Parliament,</hi> who, by ſpecious pretences of Reformation, have deceived the common people of <hi>England into deſtructive Arms, by whoſe ignorantly aſſiſting power, theſe</hi> decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Conſpirators have overthrown</hi> our admirably well-compoſed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deſtroy'd our Religion, intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced Atheiſm, and all manner of damnable Errors and Hereſies whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ruined our Liberties, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and enforcing the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:121190:50"/>their fellow-ſubjects, to kill, ſlay, and deſtroy one another, in their perſons and eſtates. <hi>Nay, ſtand ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed all the world (ſcribere palleſco)</hi> at this monſtrous relation, <hi>murdered their Soveraign, their King,</hi> the beſt and moſt religiouſly pious of Princes, endeavouring utterly to deſtroy root and branch his Royall Poſterity; rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, <hi>ſpoiling, giving, ſelling away,</hi> his Royall Revenues, and Prince-like Palaces: Extirpating the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Civill Government, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly plundering the Church of Biſhops, Paſtors, and Patrimony; the Kingdom of Religion, Liberty, Peace, and Truth, <hi>turning the pious and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable gifts</hi> of former Ages, from the Donor's firſt religious intents, into irreligious rewards of their fellow-confederates, for their bloody ſervice.</p>
            <p>Now, my too too forward ſinfull Country-men, <hi>Do you well, think you,</hi> to ſubſcribe your approbation and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſiſtance to theſe things—? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no. O therefore, if you have (as certainly you have) offended with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in denying, not onely your temporall earthly Soveraign, but your heavenly King and Lord; theſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121190:51"/>lines (like that admoniſhing Cock) thus giving you notice of your errors, Go out with him, repent, and weep bitterly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi>—; that is, I, a free-born Engliſh-man; free,<note place="margin">Engagem.</note> in reſpect of my dear So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign's protection of my ſelf, life, and eſtate, by direction of the written Lawes of the Land; in which, as my native inheritance, I have an undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed right and propriety, by which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am differenced from a ſlave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet I</hi> (notwithſtanding theſe bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks of my freedom) <hi>do ſubject my ſelf, life, and eſtate, to the arbitrary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> perverſe reſolutions, wicked actions, <hi>and corrupt affections of theſe * men, whoſe will are their Lawes, whoſe Religion is Rebellion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Faction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ep.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe Faith is Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> whoſe protection is deſtruction, whose preſervation <hi>is deſolation,</hi> whoſe juſtice <hi>is tyranny and oppreſſion,</hi> whoſe greateſt mercy <hi>is the extreamity of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. And ſhall I commend you</hi> for ſuch your ſubſcriptions? No, I commend you not, but rather adviſe you to be mindfull, how much herein you have degenerated from the former honour of Engliſh-men; earneſtly deſiring you a laſt to return to your firſt pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121190:51"/>principles of loyall valour, and Chriſtian fortitude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the ſame is now eſtabliſhed without a King and Houſe of Lords.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Engagem.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That is,<note place="margin">King, Capell, Canterbury <hi>with the reſt. Sir.</hi> Geor. Liſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chaloner, Thomſon, <hi>Alder.</hi> Garraway.</note> as they have begun to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle it upon the already-laid foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Royall Blood, the murder of not a few Noble-men and Lords, the death and impriſonment of ſeverall reverend Biſhops, learned Doctors, and other Paſtors of the Church of Chriſt; the deſtruction of many Knights and Gentlemen, the ruine of ſome Aldermen and Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and ſeverall penitentiall deceived perſons, firſt of their own party, with the loſſe of many thouſand Engliſh-men's lives; all whoſe bloods have been ſhed to mix with the curſed * Lime of theſe perſons; by which,<note place="margin">Deſignes.</note> with the additionall aſſiſtance of their ſacrilegious Church-plunderings, they ſuppoſe their uſurped power wil be the cloſer cemented. But, good Father, cut them off in the height of their hopes; let not theſe bloody men proſper any longer, leſt the Heathen blaſpheme and ſay, Where is the God of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the ſame is now eſtabliſhed without<note place="margin">Engagent.</note>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121190:52"/>a King and Houſe of Lords</hi>— with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King and Houſe of Lords? <hi>there is the bloody extirpation of</hi> England<hi>'s an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That is, as they reſolve,</hi> (for as yet, it is not eſtabliſhed) to accompliſh the eſtabliſhment thereof; intending (rather than reſtore the Nation to its former Government, by King, Lords, and Commons) to continue this their bloody building, upon the utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe remaining ruines of the Nobility, Gentry, Clergy, and Commons of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The corruption of the two once flouriſhing Academies,<note place="margin">Oxford. Cambridge.</note> famous for the purity of doctrine, excellency of diſcipline; now peſtered with hereſies, ſchiſms, and factions; that ſo their Church hereafter (it God ſhall ſuffer them, for the puniſhment of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> ſins, long to continue) may be as apt to inſtruct the people in all manner of errours, as they to govern them by all kind of wicked rules of policy. Upon the ruine of all Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, deſtruction of all Arts, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of all Schools and Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of good education; that ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may be once more famous,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121190:52"/>or rather infamous, in this Nation, and we again ſhake hands with the Papiſts; concluding Ignorance to be the mother of Devotion, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees confirming the common people into a belief of ſuch blind doctrins.</p>
            <p>Upon the utter extirpation of the purity of the Goſpell, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox preachers thereof, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing ignorant Lay-men to be directors of others toward heaven; when (too ſad a truth it is) they know not how to ſet one true ſtep forward, leading undoubtedly thither them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; until at laſt all divine Precepts ſhall be commanded attendance upon their principles of Policy, and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at laſt, by their means, uſher in the <hi>Pope, and his whole Antichriſtian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> the only way of his re-enter; for be aſſured, all the back doors are wide open, ready for his re-admiſſion, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanting, but a fit opportunity for his more generally viſible appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; for long he hath, and at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtill doth covertly walk; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times under a ſilly Independent long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſted doublet, ſometimes ruffling it in a long ſword, watching his, &amp;c. for entrance upon <hi>England</hi>'s ſtage.</p>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:121190:53"/>
            <p>Again, upon the breach of all the priviledges of Corporations,<note place="margin">Protege Londinum Domine.</note> upon which ruſh in a confuſion of Trades, and poverty unawares thereupon ſtealeth upon City and Country; and, by this,<note place="margin">Per ſcelera ſemper ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leribus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſtiter.</note> the Faction gain ſouldiers, their onely ſupporters.</p>
            <p>Nay, much I fear, their deſperate reſolves may extend to the firing of Cities, Towns, Villages; a promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous deſtruction of whole Families, not minding the innocent cries of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, the wooing tears of the Widow and Fatherleſſe, the pittifull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the Aged; becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, paſſed beyond the limits of reconciliation, never reſolving upon repentance, will not apprehend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure, but by the additionall commiſſion of greater ſins. But, O Lord God Almighty, let not theſe wicked men have their deſire. Reſcue thy poor diſtreſſed flock from theſe devouring woolves. Protect thine own Vine, the truly Chriſtian Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all members thereof, from the rooting Bores of the Antichriſtian Forreſt, &amp; the deſtroying wiles of ſubtle Foxes; that ſo they may live to praiſe thy
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121190:53"/>Name from generation to generation, whoſe mercies endure for forever.</p>
            <p>Thus having made it plainly appear, that the very act of ſubſcription to the <hi>Engagement</hi> is abſolutely unlawfull, as alſo, that without a ſerious repentance, the Subſcribers wil pul upon themſelves the guilt of a complication of all thoſe monſtrous ſins, already committed by the Grandees of the bloody Faction.</p>
            <p>And if they actually perſiſt therein by their actions, adhereing to them, will be liable to give an account for all the innocent Engliſh blood, that, for the future ſhall be ſhed by theſe deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rooters. Beſides, they will but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue inſtrumentall ſupporters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard</hi>'s continuing miſeries, if not haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning procurers of its utter deſolation; Which, may the God of heaven, out of his infinite mercy, prevent.</p>
            <p>But here I meet with an Objection, or rather a propounded Queſtion.</p>
            <p>What would you have me do? I am but one. Should I not ſubſcribe the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement,</hi> and ſwim in the ſame ſtream with each ſucceſſive faction; I fear that I ſhould loſe my eſtare.</p>
            <p>O my Brethren, a ſtrange Queſtion! That is a cheap Religion ſure, of little
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121190:54"/>eſteem, that muſt rather be parted with than a little pelf to preſerve it. Are your ſouls of no greater value, than thus eternally to be battered away upon grounds of fear, that you ſhall loſe your wealth, which cannot benefit you after death? Remember and weigh well that place, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. There, among other ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, you ſhall find, that the fearfull are caſt into hell; that is, ſuch, who, for fear of men, loſſe of their eſtates, will bid adieu to the God of heaven, and his commands.</p>
            <p>You could, in the beginning of this bloody war, upon no rationall grounds, but vain pretences of Polititians, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you for their own ends, One it, and One it freely, in your perſons and purſes, even untill many united, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed themſelves into ſeverall Armies.</p>
            <p>And now finding your ſelves ſo much abuſed and deceived by theſe Rooters, can you not One it in your return, by a ſerious and fuddain repentance? Do you think the way to pacifie an angry God, is, to add ſin to ſin? There is no peace to the wicked, faith he by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and can you expect publick, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, externall, or internall peace, if you continue in your wickedneſſe? It is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121190:54"/>too too apparent, that you have all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and you will never be <hi>recti in curia,</hi> untill you repent; upon which conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God hath onely promiſed pardon and forgiveneſſe.</p>
            <p>Do you expect to be reſtored to the re-injoyment of freedom and liberty in your perſons and eſtates, which you can onely challenge by vertue of the Laws eſtabliſhed (your certain-protectors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Inſtruments of tyranny and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion) while you tamely thus ſit crouching under their perſons, whoſe ſtudied work it is to tyrannize over all Laws, your eſtates, liberties, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, loading you with ſucceſſive Taxes, which would crack the patience of the moſt patient, and cannot but at laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſt the wealth of them, who, as yet, are accounted the moſt wealthy.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. Witneſſe <hi>K.</hi> March from <hi>Scot.</hi> to fatall <hi>Worceſt.</hi>
               </note> me-thinks I hear another ſort of people, as Governours of Cities, Forts, Caſtles, Admiralls, &amp;c. pleading, that they are entruſted by the preſent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and we muſt not betray our truſt.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, Know thus much, That if the Truſtors be juſtly poſſeſſed of what they entruſt others with, none are then to betray their truſt, by delivery of what they are truſted with, to any man that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121190:55"/>hath not right thereunto. But if theſe Truſtors have no right themſelves, nor can lay a juſt claim to the poſſeſſion of what they entruſt others with; but (of right, juſtice, and equity) the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to another; then it concerneth any man ſo truſted, in conſcience, juſtice, and equity, to deliver them to ſuch who have a right title thereunto; otherwiſe, the truſted will make themſelves doubly guilty; of deteining what is not their own, by their own confeſſion, from the juſt owner; and alſo of patronizing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo in their unjuſt poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>To apply this. How many, contrary to their own judgments, have kept poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Majeſty's Ships, Caſtles, Forts, and Towns, who, being ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd to a reſtoration, of what theſe imployed Inſtruments unjuſtly detained from him,<note place="margin">Fatall <hi>Worceſt.</hi>
               </note> their greateſt reaſon of refuſall was, Becauſe they were truſted— and what, ſhall they betray their truſt?</p>
            <p>Hear, you ſelf deceiving, and ſoul-deſtroying Pleaders— let me expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate with you: Should a man entruſt you with ſtollen goods, could you keep them from the juſt owners, onely upon this ſlender plea, becauſe you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted? — No, no, the Law, you
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121190:55"/>know, comprehendeth you, equally guilty of theft. The caſe is all one, onely admitting this diſtinction; This is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate theft, the other publick, a robbery of an higher nature, becauſe the injur'd concern'd perſons are of an higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, the King, nay, the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: and condemn'd both by the Law of God and man. The command is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, <hi>Thou ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t not ſteal.</hi> Now theft is nothing elſe but a taking away, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining contrary to Law, that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to another, purpoſely to deprive him of it, contrary to his will and mind.</p>
            <p>You plead a truſt committed; Shew me the eſtabliſhed Law, that gave them power to truſt you with his Majeſty's Caſtles, Towns, Ships, &amp;c. By the plain Letter and equity of the Law, they belong to the King, upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, his demand of reſtitution was juſt.</p>
            <p>Neither you nor your imployers have a juſt right or title thereunto by the Law; therefore you are but robbers of the King and Kingdom. By you, his Majeſty is detained from his juſt rights, his ſubjects from their liberties and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121190:56"/>eſtates; hereſie, ſchiſm, and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are continued; perjury, blood, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; and a connivance at, if not a toleration of, all manner of ſins in the Nation, and thereby you are guilty of the breach of all the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Remember that Curſe, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 27. <hi>Curſed is he that hindereth the right of the ſtranger, fatherleſſe, and widow.</hi> And, <hi>Curſed is he that continueth not in all things that are written in the Law to do them.</hi> That is, Curſed is he that knowingly, reſolvedly, wilfully, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all or any of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as the faction have done, to compaſſe their ends—. Lord have mercy upon ſinfull <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But I will draw towards a concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore by way of a brief recapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denyed, but that, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the premiſed rules of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as a man; Religion, as a Chriſtian, Proteſtant; and eſtabliſhed Laws, both the guide and protection of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects:</p>
            <p>That the Plotters, and continuing adhearers to this deſigne, are guilty of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121190:56"/>all the afore-mentioned fins.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider further, that out of neceſſity you muſt repent, in a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſenſe, as Men; in a religious ſenſe, as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Confider alſo the vanity of ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, there will be truth, peace, and proſperity in this Nation, without this double repentance.</p>
            <p>To invite you hereunto, pray ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ponder the exemplary judgments of God upon Nations, Families, Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, for their obſtinate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in known ſins; read <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapters; <hi>Zephnia</hi> the 1<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> chapter; nay, all the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, are full in examples and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, executed upon, and threatned againſt, impenitentiall ſinners.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider, that a partiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance will not ſerve the turn, ſuch as hath been the repentance of too many of your leading Presbyterians, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn not to thoſe Chriſtian Principles from whence they at firſt did deviate, but to the Covenant,<note place="margin">Scot's Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>venant.</note> in their firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun bloody deſtructive ſenſe, of alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a lawfully eſtabliſhed Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by force; of which ſort, the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121190:57"/>Prophet complaineth, that many did return, but not to the God of heaven; ſo they return, but it is onely to their private intereſts, or publick faction, to which they at firſt adheared; they would ſeem to ſerve God by an out-ſide repentance, but are really ſervants to the Beliall of the Presbyterian firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider the vanity of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſucceſſe as argumentative, to make Good the War on the Faction's part, or Juſt; therefore entitle not God as an approver of your actions, becauſe of ſucceſſe—</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of Reaſon, as men; becauſe a multitude, by united powers, may overcome a leſſer number, were their cauſe never ſo juſt.</p>
            <p>That, in that ſenſe, the Turks and Heathens, in their almoſt continuall prevalency againſt the Chriſtians, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by their numerous Armies, may be ſuppoſed to have the better cauſe— which is no leſſe than blaſphemy to maintain.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe conſider, the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall probability of <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s, and the Faction's ſucceſſe, having, by decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121190:57"/>policy, as I have already ſhewed, gained a Power: Inregard that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of their Souldiers (let them pretend what they pleaſe) fight not out of an affection to parties, but in a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary way as meer Souldiers (a Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne of this Nation) as if bloud and murder were a lawfull trade; and the Scripture, like an Almanack out of date, to be lay'd a ſide in the time of Warre.</p>
            <p>Again, the Faction alwayes had, and ſtill poſſeſſe, all poſſible means ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this end. As at firſt, in having the Command of <hi>London,</hi> that Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin of mony and men, and with them a great part of the Nation, and now all under their power: beſides his Majeſty's Revenues; Pallaces; Biſhops lands; the Eſtates of many of his loyall-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; Exciſe, and other Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; by which helps, the Faction hath rather bought victories than really fought for them; the Silver Bullet bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying more of the King's Army alive in priſons, than the Enemy's Cannons did ever wound in the field.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider that his Majeſtie's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty excepting ſome few Judaſſes, did fight
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121190:58"/>out of a religious Conſcienciouſneſſe, &amp; loyall affection to their God, Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and Country; and not for a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniary reward onely.</p>
            <p>Conſider alſo, that his Majeſty wanted thoſe means and wayes of procuring men and mony, which the Faction had alwayes in aboundance.</p>
            <p>That his armies were but as an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; the Faction's numerous.</p>
            <p>However, take ſerious notice that the King and his party have Scripture, Reaſon, and Law, on their Side; but the Faction, neither. Therefore look to it, you Continuing Sinfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herers. Never did National Sinns long eſcape the heavy hand of an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging God; and if England— Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, expect to be freed, their hopes will deceive them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>— 1, 2 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jerem</hi> 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Further, Conſider the Vanity of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſucceſs alſo; a way of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the worſt of actions. In reſpect of religion as Chriſtians; The people of God almoſt in all ages having been worſted in that reſpect. God's intent in ſuffering the enemyes of his Church
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121190:58"/>to prevail being only to try the faith and patience of his children, to make them humble,<note place="margin">Acts 14.22. Gal. 6.14.</note> fitting them thereby for Himſelfe. In reſpect of their Eternall well being in heaven, and in reference to his owne honour upon earth, that ſo his People coming as it were like pure gold out of the furnace of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they may be as ſhining and burning lamps for after-ages to walk by.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider that the flock of Chriſt alwayes was little; therefore to have Suceſſe by power of a multitude, is no argument of being Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>That (as I have already inſerted) for the moſt part the Church was under Perſecution and affliction; therefore Proſperity is no ground of Saintſhip, as the Faction pretend. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12 2. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>Be adviſed, therefore, my dear Country-men; beware of acting and maintaining any thing againſt right Reaſon: In it ſelf both a ſin and a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>How many men, ſo contrary to common ſenſe and reaſon, did, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the deceiving ſenſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, account, and highly cry up,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121190:59"/>
               <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s marching into <hi>Scotland?</hi> No invaſion of that Kingdom; where he could not ground the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a quarrell,<note place="margin">1650.</note> in his own unjuſt conſtruction; the end of his march being onely in proſecution of his firſt reſolv'd-upon Deſigne of ruining his Majeſty and Royall Family, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troying our and their Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, only to mount himſelf into the chair of Supremacy.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, many were poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſuch a ſottiſh kind of ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Futall</hi> Worceſt.</note> (a ſure preſager of utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) as to eſteem his majeſty's laſt March out of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> (with reſolves only to Regain his right and that he might reſtore his ſubjects to their Religion Laws and Liberties) to be an Invaſion of England, O <hi>Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Anglia, quae vos dementia cepit!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be for the future, therefore, adviſed, keep cloſer to the Scriptures and right reaſon: Approve, follow, and act no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what they warrant, or is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible from them: for if you once but ſlipp from that firm Square, you Tumble from once errour to another, like a man fallen from the top of a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121190:59"/>Steep hill, never reſting untill you come to the bottom; where, without the Infinitely preſerving mercy of God, you will receive the reward of Such your wilfull Neglect, even deſtruction. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 12,<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>verſes,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, If God ſhould continue ſtill puniſhing England, beware of making your ſelves Inſtrumentall-ſcourging Rodds in his hands; which, his will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing performed, he alwaies caſteth into the fire. But, O holy bleſſed and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Trinity, have mercy upon us mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners: Remember not, Lord, our offences, nor the offences of our forefathers; neither take thou any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vengeance of our ſinnes: ſpare us, good Lord, ſpare thy people whom thou haſt redeem'd with thy precious bloud, and be not angry with us for ever—. To this pupoſe we beſeech thee to give us true repentance, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us all our Sinnes, negligences, and ignorances; and to endue us with the grace of thy holy Spirit, to amend our lives acording to thy holy Word.</p>
            <p>For my part, I call heaven and earth to witneſſe; I have now ſett before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing;
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121190:60"/>Chooſe life; for why will you dy, O England? why will you deſtroy your ſelves, O people of Great Brittain? Why will you not turn to the God of heaven, with whom are treaſures of mercy? O ye Citizens of <hi>London;</hi> Turn ye, Turn ye, from your evill wayes by a ſerious ſuddain &amp; unfeigned repentance, that ſo God may return unto us in loving kindneſſe, by reſtoring to us our Governours as in former dayes,<note place="margin">K. <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </note> and cauſe us again to fit peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably under our owne vines; That our religion in purity, may practically be revived; That we may enjoy Paſtors and Teachers that may again feed us with true knowledge &amp; underſtanding; That our lawes and liberties may be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: That <hi>Great Brittain</hi> may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from this Imminent and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Menacing Ruine— That God may be glorified in our preſervation and not in our abſolute deſtruction.</p>
            <p>That all our Souls at the great day of Account may be everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſaved.</p>
            <closer>Amen, Amen, Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121190:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
